<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<title>Peter Krautzberger</title>
	<subtitle> · on the web</subtitle>
	<link href="https://www.peterkrautzberger.org/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
	<link href="https://www.peterkrautzberger.org/"/>
	<updated>2020-10-06T22:00:00+02:00</updated>
	<id>https://www.peterkrautzberger.org/</id>
	<author>
		<name>Peter Krautzberger</name>
		<email>p.krautzberger@gmail.com</email>
	</author>
	
	<entry>
		<title>Experimenting with fractions for the web</title>
		<link href="https://www.peterkrautzberger.org/0205/"/>
		<updated>2018-05-28T22:00:00+02:00</updated>
		<id>https://www.peterkrautzberger.org/0205/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I just got back from a week in San Jose at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://aimath.org/workshops/upcoming/webmath/&quot;&gt;AIM workshop on web accessibility of mathematics&lt;/a&gt;. It was an intense week for me and there&#39;s a ton to write about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This morning I came back to something I had drafted after Joanmarie Diggs proposed a session on a particular hack (but the group didn&#39;t end up focusing on this in the unconference-style workshop setting).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;That&#39;s not a fraction. &lt;em&gt;That&#39;s&lt;/em&gt; a fraction!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of my &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.peterkrautzberger.org/0205/0199/&quot;&gt;go&lt;/a&gt;-&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.peterkrautzberger.org/0205/0196/&quot;&gt;to&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.peterkrautzberger.org/0205/0192/&quot;&gt;examples&lt;/a&gt; when explaining that Presentation MathML is devoid of semantics is the &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;mfrac&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; element. While it clearly hints at being a fraction, the spec itself &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.w3.org/TR/2014/REC-MathML3-20140410/chapter3.html#presm.mfrac&quot;&gt;clearly states&lt;/a&gt; that it is not, semantically, a fraction but that it may be used for completely different things that visually look like fractions, e.g., binomial coefficients or the Legendre symbol; in fact, you can find many even less fraction-like examples (such as logical deductions) in the wild because a vertical stack with a properly aligned line is simply a neat layout feature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since Presentation MathML never specifies semantics, let&#39;s look how Content MathML encodes fractions. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.w3.org/TR/2014/REC-MathML3-20140410/chapter4.html#contm.cn&quot;&gt;spec&lt;/a&gt; would have you write something like &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;cn type=&amp;quot;rational&amp;quot;&amp;gt;22&amp;lt;sep/&amp;gt;7&amp;lt;/cn&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;. It&#39;s a terribly good example for how Content MathML is a bit too strong in its abstraction for human communication (also, check the transcription to Presentation MathML). As an aside, if you need more examples of why &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;mfrac&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; is not meaningful, just search that section.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Hacking tips for accessibility experiments&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, at the workshop Joanie had proposed the following. It turns out, Firefox is &lt;s&gt;too lazy&lt;/s&gt; &lt;em&gt;ahem&lt;/em&gt; too performance-oriented to sanitize invalid ARIA roles. This allows you to experiment with made-up properties fairly easily (assuming you can modify your screenreader of choice).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So for example, you could slap an &lt;code&gt;aria-math&lt;/code&gt; attribute to your markup and this would show up in OS-level accessibility inspectors such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.paciellogroup.com/resources/aviewer/&quot;&gt;aViewer&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://help.gnome.org/users/accerciser/stable/introduction.html.en&quot;&gt;accerciser&lt;/a&gt;. What Joanie had in mind (I believe) is that we could have tried to expose additional information this way so that Joanie could hack something into &lt;a href=&quot;https://help.gnome.org/users/orca/stable/index.html.en&quot;&gt;ORCA&lt;/a&gt; and then get Mick and Reef to modify &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nvaccess.org/&quot;&gt;NVDA&lt;/a&gt; or David to modify &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.chromevox.com/&quot;&gt;ChromeVox&lt;/a&gt; (and maybe even hear what Glen thinks of it from a JAWS perspective). And yes, all these incredible people were actually there in person.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;To fractinity, and beyond!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since an idea that I had proposed to the group (exploring web components for mathematical documents) also didn&#39;t stick, I thought I&#39;d combine the two when I get the chance. Luckily, I had a long flight home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Et voilà&lt;/span&gt;, a custom element fraction that adds &lt;code&gt;aria-math&lt;/code&gt; roles to itself magically (using &lt;code&gt;fraction&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;numerator&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;denominator&lt;/code&gt; and&lt;code&gt;fraction-line&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p data-height=&quot;265&quot; data-theme-id=&quot;0&quot; data-slug-hash=&quot;MGdmQj&quot; data-default-tab=&quot;html,result&quot; data-user=&quot;pkra&quot; data-embed-version=&quot;2&quot; data-pen-title=&quot;AIM Workshop custom element: fraction&quot; class=&quot;codepen&quot;&gt;See the Pen &lt;a href=&quot;https://codepen.io/pkra/pen/MGdmQj/&quot;&gt;AIM Workshop custom element: fraction&lt;/a&gt; by Peter Krautzberger (&lt;a href=&quot;https://codepen.io/pkra&quot;&gt;@pkra&lt;/a&gt;) on &lt;a href=&quot;https://codepen.io/&quot;&gt;CodePen&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://static.codepen.io/assets/embed/ei.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s not much and not really a &amp;quot;document&amp;quot;-level element as I was thinking about (then again, Joanie had hoped for improving an &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;mfrac&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; directly) but it&#39;s a nice (non-functional) concept, and perhaps helpful when thinking about ARIA &lt;code&gt;role-description&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>Booles&#39; Rings is dead, long live Booles&#39; Rings!</title>
		<link href="https://www.peterkrautzberger.org/0206/"/>
		<updated>2018-05-30T22:00:00+02:00</updated>
		<id>https://www.peterkrautzberger.org/0206/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, &lt;a href=&quot;http://scoskey.org/&quot;&gt;Sam&lt;/a&gt; and I removed all remaining WordPress installations that we were hosting for people that are part of &lt;a href=&quot;https://boolesrings.org/&quot;&gt;Booles&#39; Rings&lt;/a&gt;, including the original multisite installations that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.peterkrautzberger.org/0069/&quot;&gt;started it all&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Booles&#39; Rings is dead&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My regular meetings with Sam are one of my great pleasures. Since our friendship is almost exclusively virtual, it&#39;s surprising that we have kept it alive for quite a while now. Almost weekly, we get on video to work on new ideas or and projects - or just chitchat about life, work and being young parents (or parents of young kids anyway).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps unsurprisingly given that we met at a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.peterkrautzberger.org/0054/&quot;&gt;Young Set Theory Workshop&lt;/a&gt;, it all started with us setting up Set Theory Talks which grew turned into &lt;a href=&quot;http://settheory.mathtalks.org/&quot;&gt;settheory.mathtalks.org&lt;/a&gt; (and you can get a subdomain with the same semi-automatic features if you like). Nowadays, &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.assafrinot.com/&quot;&gt;Assaf&lt;/a&gt; is handling the real work of grooming the site while Sam and I continue the little bits of technical support as needed. Later, I pulled Sam into maintaining &lt;a href=&quot;https://mathblogging.org/&quot;&gt;mathblogging.org&lt;/a&gt; with me after Fred and Felix dropped out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I suppose it was inevitable ever since I left research 6 years ago.  But, really, life just got busier and hosting more complex so late last year, Sam and I decided that we do not have the time (nor the abilities) to continue hosting more and more sites. We let everyone know what&#39;s happening and helped them in their transitions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, we pulled the plug on all the WordPress goodness we had built over the years. And thus, Booles&#39; Rings has passed - in its original form, a literal network of WordPress sites for academics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Long live Booles&#39; Ring!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, none of the sites have disappeared. In many ways we&#39;re now where I wanted to get everyone to: not just researchers taking the web seriously as a fixed point of a research career, building a stable presence of one&#39;s research persona, overcoming the cacophony of ever-changing, dead-or-dying department pages where Google page rank inevitably yields the outdated ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No, I always wanted more: get researchers to take this platform seriously, embrace it as a medium with new (and old) idiosyncrasies. Take it seriously as a tool that you should wield confidently and, in need, wield independently, no matter what. No more lock in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And this is where Booles&#39; Rings is now. The people are still here, the site now merely works as lightweight connection (and an aggregator). And no matter how we all approach this medium, it&#39;s fine. Whether it&#39;s self-hosted WordPress installations or statically generated sites, whether slow-churning long form or near-daily activity, whether research-only or life&#39;s breadth. The point is not that one thing is better than the other. The point is that we are on the web, our shared and world wide web - and that we&#39;re here to stay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even though I left research years ago, I still love to follow this community. I look forward to the next 7 years of Booles&#39; Rings.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>6 Thoughts on accessibility of equation layout</title>
		<link href="https://www.peterkrautzberger.org/0207/"/>
		<updated>2018-10-27T22:00:00+02:00</updated>
		<id>https://www.peterkrautzberger.org/0207/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;q&gt;Of course it is more complicated than that.&lt;/q&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Isn&#39;t it always?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;button onclick=&quot;document.body.innerHTML = body.innerHTML.replace(/equation/g,&#39;formula&#39;);&quot;&gt;Replace &lt;em&gt;equation&lt;/em&gt; with &lt;em&gt;formula&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/button&gt;, if you prefer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;The first rule of equation layout accessibility&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don&#39;t talk about &amp;quot;math accessibility&amp;quot; when you mean equation layout accessibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mathematics is an ancient domain of human knowledge, formula or equation layout a visual layout technique developed primarily in the 19th and 20th century.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mathematical content is far more than content that needs equation layout and equation layout appears in many more domains than just mathematics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will fail to make equation layout accessible if we think we can treat equation layout identically across mathematics, physics, chemistry, computer science, biology etc (and their various sub-fields). For example, voicing a superscript 2 as &amp;quot;squared&amp;quot; may be a reasonable heuristic for middle school mathematics but a miserable heuristic for chemistry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will fail to make mathematical content accessible if we only make equation layout accessible and vice versa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;2. Augmentation is a must (or: &lt;em&gt;aria-labels must work&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Manually overriding accessible name calculations (e.g., via aria-label) on text(-like) content is generally considered a last resort and it is clearly not a long term strategy for accessibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But we have aria-labels because we know from experience that there&#39;s always a situation where you need them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently, it is extremely hard to augment equation layout with aria-labels let alone anything beyond simple overrides. This is a problem of authoring but much more of rendering and assistive technologies. MathML-based solutions in browsers and AT are particularly bad at this and to some degree this cannot be fixed (we should get to that later).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whatever solutions might arise in the future of equation layout, like everything else on the web, they must be able to work together with interspersed aria-labels, together with potentially many interspersed aria-labels, and ultimately with only aria-labels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words, &lt;em&gt;deep aria labels&lt;/em&gt; aka &lt;em&gt;aria labels all the way down&lt;/em&gt; must work as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a problem as ARIA has limitations when it comes to exposing custom tree structures and making them explorable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More general author-driven augmentation must also work. Equation layout may have a natural tree structure derived from the DOM but we must be able to modify that. Aria-owns might be a solution here but right now it appears to too limited (either by spec or implementations).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;3. Visual quality must come first (and that&#39;s a problem)&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If equation layout is visually inadequate, it cannot be considered accessible. The problem is: we have no solid basis for measuring this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While TeX-style layout is generally considered the &lt;em&gt;highest quality&lt;/em&gt; among heavy users of equation layout, there seems to be no research evaluating this from an accessibility point of view. For example, TeX layout is largely unconcerned with K12 content and (as a print technology) has no concept for the kind of dynamic modifications we can realize on the web. While there are minor variations, e.g., elementary education preferring sans-serif fonts and requiring fonts with an open glyph for 4, it&#39;s unclear to me in how far these preferences are evidence-based (pointers very welcome); in any case, they are also deeply rooted in print and might be moot on the web, e.g., there might be better ways for get whatever effect such variations are supposed to achieve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the web, it probably means that equation layout must be flexible enough to allow all kinds of (user or author enabled) customizations. Some obvious questions: What should happen when the line-height changes? The letter spacing? When a transform or animation is applied to a descendant? A color changes on something with a specific color? A font (style) changes on a mathvariant? These all might be useful for accessibility purposes (e.g., with visual impairments, learning disabilities). And there are likely many more things we cannot imagine yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think we greatly lack research as to what features in visual layout might be important for accessibility &lt;em&gt;on the web&lt;/em&gt;. Without such research, we have no adequate basis on which to discuss improvements to equation layout and the standards that enable it on the web.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;4. Heuristics should be used at authoring time&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Heuristics are important across the assistive technology chain to recover from bad input (content). However, heuristics should not be necessary with &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt; markup, e.g., markup that is ideal according to specs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Equation layout is tremendously ambiguous, primarily due to its history and the limitations of print technology. For example, it is near impossible to differentiate the typical vertical fraction layout from the various other notations that share a similar vertical stack (2-3 children, depending on a line in between).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words, even high quality markup for equation layout requires heavy use of heuristics to guess the semantics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Heuristics for non-visual representation of equation layout have existed for a very long time (and before the web). Today, some assistive technologies integrate heuristics for equation layout when done as MathML markup.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a problem because most of these heuristics are fairly bad. Heuristics for equation layout are largely of low quality at scale. It is unsurprising when (e.g.) Nemeth&#39;s math speak rules were invented for a person reading to another; such limitations could easily be overcome in that situations. At the scale of the web, it is much easier to run into edge cases where heuristics are too coarse or too fine grained. An almost universal limitation is the restrictions to individual fragments of equation layout, ignoring the context (both equational and otherwise).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Relying on heuristics in AT for &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt; content poses a serious issue (hinted to earlier): heuristics interfere with augmentation. For example, the commonly used heuristic that every superscript 2 is voiced &lt;q&gt;square&lt;/q&gt;, then no override may be possible; even if it is, will an override override the phrasing (e.g., &lt;q&gt;to the power of two&lt;/q&gt;) or also consider the superscript position? Do you need two overrides to clarify? If a heuristic identifies (1+2+3) as a summation and provides summary information (e.g. &lt;q&gt;sum with three summands&lt;/q&gt;), what happens when an author augment one of the + signs (say, with &lt;code&gt;aria-label=&amp;quot;times&amp;quot;&lt;/code&gt;)?  We would need to augment both the content and the heuristics. As the saying goes: and now we have two problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much like with textual descriptions of other visual content (e.g., image alttext, video captions, SVG descriptions) heuristical tools (human or machine guided) should be used at authoring time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;5. Describing layout is a red herring&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a position that I encounter every once in a while: just give non-visual users access to the visual layout and stop. That&#39;s a very appealing proposition: instead of trying to make sense of visual layout semantically, we &lt;em&gt;just&lt;/em&gt; provide information about what letter/word is where on a two-dimensional canvas. It also appeals to a basic idea of equality: visual users only have visual access, why would non-visual users get additional information?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, it is a red herring: it is neither easy nor helpful nor what anyone has ever done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is obviously not easy on the web because layout is dynamic; if two users read a document on two different devices, they might have a very different idea as to what is where. Even within equation layout, automatic linebreaking/reflow can shift parts around, more advanced methods (e.g., MathJax&#39;s collapsing feature) can vary even more greatly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But ignoring this larger problem, traditional equation layout has a few odd concepts that make this even more difficult. For example, movable limits can move elements from sub/superscript positions to under/overscript positions based on the context of a subexpression, without any change in the markup; reversely, this can happen when changing text content (thanks to things like the operator dictionary). Another example is the concept of embellished operators which make it difficult to identify reasonable layout blocks to describe; similarly, brackets may or may not be marked up in a way that groups open and closing brackets. Essentially, you will still need to analyze the layout &lt;em&gt;semantically&lt;/em&gt; to identify what really belongs where and together with what because that is ultimately a question of &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a consequence, the idea of &lt;em&gt;just&lt;/em&gt; describing layout is not helpful to anyone, no matter what assistive technologies they might use (even if it&#39;s just a screen). Even more so, when you have to do the same analysis as you would for identifying semantics of an expression.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What&#39;s more important is that describing layout is not what anyone has ever done (so I would surmise nobody wanted to do it). Some layout information is always ignored, other layout is always inferred as semantic. As way back as Nemeth&#39;s math speak rules for print we have had heuristics that will read any superscript 2 as &lt;em&gt;squared&lt;/em&gt;, inferring semantics where there are none. Reversely, no assistive technology for equation layout will tell you about the dimension of a stretchy character (neither directly nor transformatively e.g. via audio cues). Again, a good example is a movable limit where rule sets get around describing (unreliable) layout in favor of heuristically determined semantics, e.g., in a sum they might voice &lt;q&gt;sum from [subscript] to [superscript]&lt;/q&gt;, neatly avoiding the layout. Above all, human beings do not speak equation layout as layout. Nobody says &lt;q&gt;vertical bar A vertical bar&lt;/q&gt; they say absolute value or determinant or something completely different, nobody says &lt;q&gt;C O subscript 2&lt;/q&gt; they say CO2 or carbon dioxide or possibly some more precise wording if it appears inside a checmical equation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, describing visual layout is nevertheless a decent fallback mechanism, e.g., when semantic heuristics fail but you can still recover layout information and it is important to be able to enable users to explore the layout if they need to (e.g., so as to reproduce it for their own work). But edge cases should not limit the expressiveness of accessible equation layout in general.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(An independent issue is to expose layout so that a user can guess how something was authored (e.g., when voicing gives you &lt;q&gt;determinant A&lt;/q&gt;, the questions may be if it was represented  visually as &lt;code&gt;det A&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;|A|&lt;/code&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;6. We must strive for multi-directionality&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Accessibility is not a one way street, equation layout even more so. Accessibility must handle directionality on many axes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Accessibility means to improve access to content no matter whether a user can access it with all theoretically possible human capacity or only using a small fragment thereof at a time. Due to its highly compressed form, equation layout requires more back and forth across a particular equation fragment as well as the entire document than most other forms of content. This is both a bug and a feature but either way it won&#39;t go away any time soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Accessibility means to improve interaction with content so as to allow all users to transfer knowledge better. Equation layout has a huge discrepancy between authoring formats and rendering. We must strive to improve this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Acccessibility means improving the interaction between human beings. If two students explore a document, they should be able to do so together so that they can engage each other. Therefore, the effects of exploring content should be equivalent between different exploration methods. At the AIM workshop earlier this year, Sam Dooley told the story of a young blind person joyously celebrating that their parent could &lt;q&gt;read my math&lt;/q&gt; as they used an accessible authoring and rendering environment together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interaction in these multiple directions will provide more information to more people, enabling wider accessibility, whether people identify as AT users or not. More importantly, it will show the path towards what the web can really do for the knowledge traditionally represented in equation layout.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>Three interesting results from the AIM workshop</title>
		<link href="https://www.peterkrautzberger.org/0208/"/>
		<updated>2018-11-14T23:00:00+01:00</updated>
		<id>https://www.peterkrautzberger.org/0208/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;When I look back at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.peterkrautzberger.org/0201/&quot;&gt;looking ahead to 2018&lt;/a&gt;, I&#39;m going to fall short of my goals for this year. Life was on full throttle this year; no regrets. But I want to at least acknowledge what an excellent adventure the &lt;a href=&quot;https://aimath.org/webmath&quot;&gt;AIM Workshop&lt;/a&gt; in May has been. So let&#39;s take a look at three interesting results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The first rule of workshops&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s all in the people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, the very best part of this workshop was the people who attended it. It&#39;s amazing to get people from NVDA, JAWS and ChromeVox into a room for a few days. It&#39;s even better when you have people from MathJax, MathLive, Desmos in the same room. It gets even better when you have publishing experts from Wiley and Pearson on board. It&#39;s incredibly much better to have the vast expertise of people such as T.V. Raman and Joanie Diggs there. But for me, the most thrilling was the educators in the room. They are the key and without them we are all lost. And I&#39;m the first to admit the workshop didn&#39;t serve them well enough. Even more importantly, at future workshops we need to get students in the room as well. Because what the hell are we doing without them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In extension, this is a compliment to AIM&#39;s workshop design. Providing funding not only for a workshop but for everyone&#39;s travel and accommodation was excellent but also crucial. We would never have been able to get all these people in a room. This is the right way to hold workshops, especially when inclusiveness is a huge issue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Towards an optional Braille stream&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&#39;s a particular limitation of today&#39;s accessibility landscape: we cannot specify separate textual alternatives for voice and Braille.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Generally, not having separate streams for voice and Braille does not seem like a huge problem. As long as all accessibility needs are covered by a fixed set of standard elements that are designed for both aural and tacticle interfaces, then assistive technologies can reliably implement a split in the stream, i.e., present separate voice and Braille streams from that. For example, if you have a dedicated button element, it can represented as a &lt;code&gt;btn&lt;/code&gt; contraction on a Braille display and voiced as &lt;em&gt;Button&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As usual, not all things can be covered by standards. Say your button is is used as a control in a game then you may want to augment the button&#39;s accessible name to include the action. So if the button opens a selection of planets to travel your to in your game, then you may want to have this voiced as &lt;em&gt;planet&lt;/em&gt;. You can do that of course and then you might get a voicing of &lt;em&gt;planet; button&lt;/em&gt; and something akin to &lt;code&gt;pln btn&lt;/code&gt; on a Braille display.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, you might find yourself in a situation where you need to prevent the addition of &lt;em&gt;button&lt;/em&gt; in the voicing because it may be problematic for your aural users, e.g., users with learning disabilities may find it to be distracting noise. But now how do you identify the button on a Braille display?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For equation layout, the situation is much like that final situation. In many countries, specialized Braille formats such as Nemeth, UEB, or Marburg have been developed to represent equation layout in Braille. These are well established and there are not too difficult to create. But they differ considerably from what you would might want to render aurally (and visually). In fact, since most precede the web, they try to capture (simplified) visual layout, including all the ambiguities we face there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me, the greatest positive experience of the workshop was to see the group assess the problem, come to an agreement that it needs a solution, &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/w3c/aria/issues/765&quot;&gt;add it to the ARIA tracker&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://sinabahram.github.io/aria-playground/CustomBrailleOutput.html&quot;&gt;build demos&lt;/a&gt; and even see NVDA whip up a first implementation that we could explore by the end of the week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was &lt;strong&gt;huge&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And yet, it is the easy part. Now the long road towards a proper standard with widespread implementations lies ahead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Progress on deep aria labels&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I brought my favorite problem to the workshop - &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.peterkrautzberger.org/0192/&quot;&gt;deep &lt;code&gt;aria-label&lt;/code&gt;s&lt;/a&gt; and I was not disappointed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Assistive technologies for equation layout (in particular for MathML) have to apply heuristics (read: guess) the semantics of an expression so that they can generate meaningful non-visual representations. This is a problem because heuristics that are hard coded into an external tool such as screenreaders cannot be altered by standard means, leaving authors without adequate means to ensure the quality of their content. (If a screenreader voices every superscripted 2 as &lt;em&gt;squared&lt;/em&gt; and you have no way of changing that, then you&#39;re screwed.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More importantly, since equation layout is, ultimately, only visual, a perfectly correct representation in HTML is as &lt;code&gt;span&lt;/code&gt;s, i.e., there are no semantics. Finally, ARIA (naturally) does not have a dictionary of equation layout terminology (let alone mathematical or scientific terminology) to use - a) because all past dictionary based approaches have failed and b) such a dictionary would have to be extensible (read: infinite) which ARIA, so far, does not really want to be (&lt;code&gt;role-description&lt;/code&gt; notwithstanding).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the pragmatic answer is: you&#39;ll just have to do it yourself and use deep &lt;code&gt;aria-label&lt;/code&gt;s: you override every single accessible name computation by slapping a fixed label to things. Because, ultimately, this is how we read equational content - with words.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The trouble is that it&#39;s easy to add a single &lt;code&gt;aria-label&lt;/code&gt; at the root but it is hard to provide an explorable structure that provides a decent user experience. You&#39;ll want to provide labels at the leaf level but the state of ARIA prevents those from adequately building up an explorable tree. (And we&#39;re not even talking about refinements such as providing summaries and structural and positional information during exploration.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the workshop, David Tseng from Google&#39;s ChromeVox team, Volker Sorge from Speech Rule Engine and Davide Cervone from MathJax sat down nd &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/zorkow/AIM-Workshop/tree/master/annotations&quot;&gt;build a first demo&lt;/a&gt; that tries two things&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;expose the semantic structure identified by Speech Rule Engine&#39;s heuristic using &lt;code&gt;aria-owns&lt;/code&gt; attribute&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;expose (some of) the detailed speech information provided by SRE&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;provide exploration of that tree via &lt;code&gt;aria-active-descendant&lt;/code&gt; manipulations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is, simply put, a fantastic step forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The approach builds on existing parts of ARIA and identifies reasonable, incremental improvements to it. It raises important questions on general exploration, e.g., how is there a generic &lt;code&gt;aria-table&lt;/code&gt; walker in every screenreader but not some basic &lt;code&gt;aria-tree&lt;/code&gt; walker (such as breadth or depth first)?. And yet it pragmatically builds an unobtrusive solution anyway that works at 60FPS. It works with any markup, in particular any approach using CSS or SVG markup. And to top it off, it leverages existing open-source tool to enrich pre-existing content. And while it shows just how far ahead MathJax and Speech Rule Engine are, this approach is transparent and easily used by any other equation layout library.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In terms of UX, this is also a critical step forward. The approach is should be able to provide a seamless an interaction for visual and non-visual users alike, in synchronization. Effectively, it pushes MathJax&#39;s Accessibility Extensions from client- to server-side, requiring minimal JavaScript (just a keyboard event listener) to expose the content, without live region hacks, and with a solid non-JS fallback. It provides a clear path for making even that bit of JS obsolete through natural improvements to ARIA. It opens a path to finally get rid of the horrible hackery such as JAWS did back in the day, manipulating IE&#39;s DOM to manipulate MathJax, or Texthelp is doing today by injecting JS on the client (yuck!, and also badly failing when content-security is in place).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even better, if you combine it with the previous part (exposing specialized Braille which SRE can soon produce), then this would immediately become the by far best, universal rendering of equation layout on the web: robust, high-quality, customizable, precise. And it is a solution that will only get better as standards evolve while leaving the full control with the author (with or without aid of heuristics at authoring time).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ll dig into this more some other time but admittedly, I&#39;m pretty excited.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Coda&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find the &lt;a href=&quot;https://aimath.org/pastworkshops/webmath.html&quot;&gt;organizers&#39; report at aimath.org&lt;/a&gt; but you can take one thing away: It&#39;s looking very good for accessible equation layout on the web these days. And it will only get better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we can continue these workshops, things will move faster for everyone. And maybe, just maybe, we can even finally move on to actual mathematics (and other STEM content) on the web.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>Towards a general method for accessible content trees or: deep aria-labels for equations revisited</title>
		<link href="https://www.peterkrautzberger.org/0209/"/>
		<updated>2019-01-12T23:00:00+01:00</updated>
		<id>https://www.peterkrautzberger.org/0209/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Oh dear, that title is a mouth full. A while ago I wrote about &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.peterkrautzberger.org/0208/&quot;&gt;two interesting results from the AIM workshop&lt;/a&gt; and I had promised to dive deeper. Well, take a deep breath.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;A simple example&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s a story. I think it was at the first web standard related event that I ever attended, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.w3.org/2012/08/electronic-books/&quot;&gt;W3C workshop on ebooks&lt;/a&gt; back in 2012. Someone (maybe Janina?) presented an example of an accessible SVG and I was blown away. My memory, flawed as it is, says it was the &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Ghostscript_Tiger.svg&quot;&gt;classic SVG tiger&lt;/a&gt; but it was set up in a way that demonstrated amazing exploration features, providing non-visual representations that could dive into the entirety of the graphic, starting with high-level descriptions (something like &lt;em&gt;a tiger&#39;s head&lt;/em&gt;) all the way down to detailed nuances (&lt;em&gt;left whisker, 3 of 12&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m prone ot get the specifics wrong so here&#39;s a different example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:House.svg#/media/File:House.svg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/2/24/House.svg&quot; alt=&quot;clip art house&quot; width=&quot;389&quot; height=&quot;391&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
By &lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow&quot; class=&quot;external text&quot; href=&quot;http://openclipart.org/media/people/barretr&quot;&gt;barretr&lt;/a&gt; (Open Clip Art Library) - &lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow&quot; class=&quot;external free&quot; href=&quot;http://openclipart.org/media/files/barretr/2941&quot;&gt;http://openclipart.org/media/files/barretr/2941&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/deed.en&quot; title=&quot;Creative Commons Zero, Public Domain Dedication&quot;&gt;CC0&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/w/index.php?curid=3454675&quot;&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So this is a house. How would you describe it? Maybe: &lt;em&gt;A house with a red chimney and a blue door&lt;/em&gt;? That&#39;s not bad but there&#39;s more so much more to be said about this house!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It&#39;s a drawing of the front of a house (no other part is visible)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it has a dark gray, mono-pitched roof with a red chimney on the left&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it has a blue door with a round, dark-gray doorknob on the left&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it has a yellow front wall&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the chimney aligns with the wall&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;some parts are drawn with gradient effects&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;...&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These descriptions could of course all be put into one very long textual representation, e.g., as a &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;title&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; or an &lt;code&gt;aria-labeledby&lt;/code&gt; construction. And that would be ok. But I find it rather limited.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not how a human would describe things. Imagine I&#39;d ask you to describe it. You would not start with the gradient of the doorknob on the first go. I bet you are much more inclined to provide some information at first and get into more detail if whoever is asking wants to dive deeper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, we are in the position to have more information like this on the web, too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine, this house was created in an authoring environment that specializes on such drawings; it may have been drag&amp;amp;dropped using pre-fabricated components, each having detailed descriptions, integrating user changes such as shape or color modifications, and being able to generate composited descriptions, perhaps combining them using simple rule sets (maybe even author customizable rule sets).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other thing you may notice is that the house is more than the sum of its parts, i.e., a description for the house (and parts thereof) may not sufficiently be represented by stringing the descriptions of the leafs together; for example, where would the &lt;em&gt;with&lt;/em&gt; in &lt;em&gt;a roof with a chimney&lt;/em&gt; come from? For that matter, where would &lt;em&gt;house&lt;/em&gt; come from? Depending on the content and context, there may be additional connecting words or phrases, there may be details to drop or reveal. Maybe the fabric of the roof or the whether the door is locked can be deduced from visual styling given other context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are lucky and you have more information, then you may find yourself in a situation where you want to add differing textual representations on every level of the tree, just like you would in a real conversation, and you may want a way for users to have access to all those varying levels of representation - but not all at once as that could be overwhelming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most important point: like all good web standards topics, this is about a general, low-level problem. (Although solving a more general problem might appeal to mathematicians, too.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Deep aria labels on tree structures (or: it&#39;s not &lt;em&gt;just&lt;/em&gt; about equations)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So let&#39;s try to outline what this is about. Imagine you have&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a complex DOM structure (e.g., an inline SVG, a complex grid structure, an equation layout thingie)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;which is not represented well by its leafs alone (e.g., there might be abstract components, abbreviated content, inferred meaning)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;that might have a semantic tree structure that does not match the DOM tree.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now imagine that you have&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;appropriate textual representations for each node (e.g., aria-labels on all nodes)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;yet those textual representations may have notable differences between non-leafs and their descendants, i.e., a node may be more than the sum of its descendants (or less or both/neither).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and you have proper aria-owns attributes all over the tree to represent the correct semantics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What to want&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&#39;s start with some fairly standard observations on accessible rendering:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Unified rendering&lt;/strong&gt; visual and non-visual rendering should not be apart. Textual representation should be intentional, reflect the intention of the author. (This does not contradict that both graphical and textual representation will likely be created with tools, even tools leveraging heuristics.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Progressive enhancement / graceful degradation&lt;/strong&gt; a solution should work in a way that allows to progressively enhance content. For example, a top-level textual description (e.g., using &lt;code&gt;aria-label&lt;/code&gt;) is a robust fallback. You may lose some convenience if that&#39;s all there is - and even some information - but it certainly isn&#39;t terrible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Performance&lt;/strong&gt; a solution must be performant, especially if you apply it to hundreds or thousands of content fragments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From an author&#39;s point of view, the key affordance is &lt;strong&gt;precision/control&lt;/strong&gt;. This is worth repeating: Accessibility inevitably starts with author control. If authors cannot create content in a way that they can trust to render reliably, i.e., with the precision they put into their content, then they will not care to do so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If there&#39;s no control, the platform is failing the authors. If it&#39;s failing the authors to create accessible content, then it&#39;s failing the user because they will not receive accessible content.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This primarily means that content should be authorable in a way that does not require &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; heuristics on the side of rendering (visually or non-visually). Imagine AT would have to guess how many items are in a list. Or AT would have to throw computer vision at each image to guess a description. That&#39;s ok for broken content but not acceptable for good content.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are other useful things of course - ease of authoring comes to mind. But without a solution with tangible benefits, building authoring tools or practices is never going to happen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From a screenreader user&#39;s point of view, there are more affordances that you probably don&#39;t want to ignore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;support for reading/browse modes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;support for full exploration (in focus mode)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;seamlessly switch between exploration and reading/browse&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;synchronization of all rendering streams
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;visual (highlighting), aural and tactile rendering&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;enable customized Braille stream if specialized Braille formats exists&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are many more considerations beyond this but this would be a good start.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Towards a solution: mathjax-sre-walker&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note&lt;/em&gt;: this is not a complete solution to all of the above. But I feel like it&#39;s heading in the right direction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The codebase for this lighweight walker dubbed mathjax-sre-walker is on GitHub and for this first public summary we&#39;ve tagged &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/krautzource/mathjax-sre-walker/releases/tag/2.0.0&quot;&gt;v2.0.0&lt;/a&gt;. As I mentioned in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.peterkrautzberger.org/0208&quot;&gt;208&lt;/a&gt;, this work with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.peterkrautzberger.org/0209/www.progressiveaccess.com/&quot;&gt;Volker Sorge&lt;/a&gt; grew out of a demo that David Tseng, Volker Sorge and Davide Cervone built at the AIM workshop in San Jose last year. A simplified demo in a codepen is embedded below alongside a recording of a quick demonstration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;what users get&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the visual user, it will provide a means of visually exploring the underlying (and often hard to discern) tree structure by putting the tree in focus and using the arrow keys.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the non-visual user, it will additionally provide textual representations for each tree node, in sync with the visual representation. It doesn&#39;t but could (should we get separate &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/w3c/aria/issues/765&quot;&gt;Braille streams in ARIA&lt;/a&gt;) additionally provide a simultaneous rendering in specialized formats such as Nemeth or UEB, chemical Braille or others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the screenreader user, it will provide the top-level tree node in browse mode. When the tree&#39;s top-level DOM node is voiced, the screenreader should put in focus, triggering visual highlighting; the screenreader should also indicate the tree role to imply further functionality is available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The user can switch to the screenreader&#39;s focus mode to use keyboard exploration with the arrow keys which is matched visually by the highlighting. When the user switches back to browse mode, they can continue naturally browsing to the next piece of content.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;how users get it&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first, not too relevant part: the DOM tree has lots of information in &lt;code&gt;data-&lt;/code&gt; attributes and in a first step we enrich the content with a secondary structure. Getting such information is of course not easy (luckily we can already automate that for equations thanks to speech-rule-engine) and this step can be done server-side. Ultimately that&#39;s not the hardest part - domain experts can build such tools - we&#39;re using Volker&#39;s &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/zorkow/speech-rule-engine/&quot;&gt;speech-rule-engine&lt;/a&gt; for the equations (which is a marvel).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet all the extra information won&#39;t help if we can&#39;t make use of it on the web platform.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So how is this realized in the DOM tree? As a bunch of &lt;code&gt;aria-label&lt;/code&gt;s (to add textual representations) and &lt;code&gt;aria-owns&lt;/code&gt; to carve out the tree structure that might differ from the DOM tree; we also add a &lt;code&gt;role&lt;/code&gt; to most nodes. In particular, we immediately get a top-level &lt;code&gt;aria-label&lt;/code&gt; which serves as a fallback.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now what we&#39;re missing is some kind of AT functionality that would give us an &lt;code&gt;aria-owns&lt;/code&gt; tree walker. We have built-in table walkers in screen readers already so this does not seem like a massive stretch to imagine, especially given the evolution of the tree role so far. Sadly, we do not have general purpose tree walkers (yet).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the second part, we overcome this by adding such a walker in JS. This walker consists of a tree structure (the &lt;code&gt;aria-owns&lt;/code&gt; tree, generated from the embedded data for performance) and a keyboard listener. It is very close to the DOM&#39;s &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/API/Treewalker&quot;&gt;treewalker API&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.w3.org/TR/wai-aria-practices-1.1/#TreeView&quot;&gt;WCAG tree examples&lt;/a&gt;, except that we&#39;re working on the &lt;code&gt;aria-owns&lt;/code&gt; tree because that tree may have a different order/structure from the DOM. This walker is fairly minimal, probably ~100 lines of ES6 code if you strip it down to its minimum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s a demo of v2 or you can look at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://krautzource.github.io/mathjax-sre-walker/index.html&quot;&gt;one in the repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p data-height=&quot;896&quot; data-theme-id=&quot;0&quot; data-slug-hash=&quot;EGOZxm&quot; data-default-tab=&quot;result&quot; data-user=&quot;pkra&quot; data-pen-title=&quot;mathjax-sre-walker v2 demo&quot; class=&quot;codepen&quot;&gt;See the Pen &lt;a href=&quot;https://codepen.io/pkra/pen/EGOZxm/&quot;&gt;mathjax-sre-walker v2 demo&lt;/a&gt; by Peter Krautzberger (&lt;a href=&quot;https://codepen.io/pkra&quot;&gt;@pkra&lt;/a&gt;) on &lt;a href=&quot;https://codepen.io/&quot;&gt;CodePen&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://static.codepen.io/assets/embed/ei.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;role role role your boat, gently down the stream&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A side note on the chosen &lt;code&gt;role&lt;/code&gt; attributes. The tree role and its related roles may appear a good fit but they have been developed for specific application-like interfaces. It might be that it&#39;s smarter to use something different here, I honestly don&#39;t know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Besides possibly being the right roles, they are also supported well across the accessibility tool chain, i.e., they happen to get the effects we&#39;d like to see.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What are those effects?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a top-level &lt;code&gt;aria-label&lt;/code&gt; to provide a default textual representation, especially in browse mode&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;deeply nested &lt;code&gt;aria-labels&lt;/code&gt; with the role &lt;code&gt;treeitem&lt;/code&gt; provide detailed textual representation of all relevant nodes in exploration in focus mode&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;browse mode puts element in focus on-the-go which makes for good UX: just drop out of browse mode when you hear an equation to start exploring&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;switching back to browse mode continues smoothly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;active-descendant&lt;/code&gt; is used to move the the focus on the accessibility tree&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;thereby exposing the nested labels instead of the top-level node&#39;s label&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other roles have too many negative side effects in practice. Perhaps they shouldn&#39;t but it&#39;s often too hard to dissect if a problem comes from the ARIA specs, browser implementations, OS APIs, or screenreaders.  For example, some approaches didn&#39;t work well on MathJax SVG output but worked well on the clip art house; this is probably due to &lt;code&gt;use&lt;/code&gt; elements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some other roles we&#39;ve tested across screenreaders:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;img&lt;/code&gt; (nested) prevents exploration&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;application&lt;/code&gt; loses the top level label when using browse mode and it is difficult to get back to browse mode after exploration&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;group&lt;/code&gt; is similar to application (except easier to get back into browse mode) but works poorly with CSS rendering&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;button&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;math&lt;/code&gt; mostly work the same as &lt;code&gt;tree&lt;/code&gt; (very wrong, but hey)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe those issues are fixable or maybe just due to my lack of understanding of specs and implementations. Of course, the mythical &lt;code&gt;role=static&lt;/code&gt; (&lt;code&gt;text&lt;/code&gt; etc.) might be very appropriate but, alas, it doesn&#39;t exist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Personally, I don&#39;t care which role I use. Whatever role works, I&#39;m happy to use it. Tree seems both adequate and semantically fitting, and they have a history of steady improvement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;In real life&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below is a recording with NVDA and Chrome on Windows 10.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;display: flex&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;720&quot; height=&quot;748&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/LWho3euldjM&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; style=&quot;flex-grow: 1&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Support&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, this works well on Firefox and Chrome while Edge and Safari generally don&#39;t get your more than the top-level label, i.e., the fallback; I haven&#39;t taken the time to compile for IE11 to test it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NVDA seems best so far, JAWS seems to have a problem tracking focus (it jumps away when getting back into browse mode / virtual cursor), and Orca &lt;s&gt;struggles with CSS rendering&lt;/s&gt; (see update below). VoiceOver with Safari is doing its thing (treating everything as a group) but VO works well with Chrome on MacOS. On iOS and Android we get the top-level labels (except VO with CSS rendering for some reason). The current code lacks touch input because (as far as I know) neither Talkback nor VoiceOver have a way to switch into (some form of) focus mode; it could be added, perhaps the visual exploration is interesting enough. I&#39;ll be publishing more demo runs as we move along.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, I&#39;m excited about the robustness at this stage and I plan to use this at work soon(ish). I also hope to bring the discussion around standardization of tree walkers to the ARIA Working Group - it seems to align with the evolution of tree widgets (e.g., for tab focus management, positional information) and a lot of content could benefit from some defaults in AT (much like with table walkers). But first we really need separate Braille streams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;update 2019-01-24&lt;/strong&gt; Joanmarie Diggs was kind enough to look into the issues with CSS layout (commits &lt;a href=&quot;https://gitlab.gnome.org/GNOME/orca/commit/9357aa9cd82f43a853704b98464eb7a76352d4ed&quot;&gt;9357aa9c&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://gitlab.gnome.org/GNOME/orca/commit/87d78dad097ce11a359e3bbebd77f5d32b2fccd6&quot;&gt;87d78dad&lt;/a&gt;) and Orca now matches NVDA beautifully.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>Carnival of Math No. 173</title>
		<link href="https://www.peterkrautzberger.org/0210/"/>
		<updated>2019-09-11T22:00:00+02:00</updated>
		<id>https://www.peterkrautzberger.org/0210/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This year I &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.peterkrautzberger.org/0194/&quot;&gt;once again&lt;/a&gt; have the pleasure to host the now &lt;strong&gt;173th Carnival of Mathematics&lt;/strong&gt;, the moveable feast of mathematical blogging shepherded by &lt;a href=&quot;http://aperiodical.com/carnival-of-mathematics/&quot;&gt;The Aperiodical&lt;/a&gt;, the best math blogging collective on this little blue ball in space. Be sure to &lt;a href=&quot;https://leeyieng.wordpress.com/2019/08/04/carnival-of-mathematics-172/&quot;&gt;visit the previous Carnival (No. 172) at Cassandra Lee Yieng&#39;s blog&lt;/a&gt; and keep an eye on &lt;a href=&quot;https://aperiodical.com/carnival-of-mathematics/&quot;&gt;all Carnivals&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As tradition will have it, we begin our show by taking a closer look at our number.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;173&lt;/strong&gt; is not just a prime, the sum of two squares of primes (2²+13²) &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; the sum of three primes (53+59+61). No, it is also a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Balanced_prime&quot;&gt;balanced prime&lt;/a&gt; (same gap to previous and following prime) and the 13&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt;(!) &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sophie_Germain_prime&quot;&gt;Sopie Germain prime&lt;/a&gt; (since 2×173+1=347 is also prime).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img width=&quot;256&quot; style=&quot;margin: 0 auto;&quot; alt=&quot;Sophie Germain&quot; src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/8/8b/Germain.jpeg&quot;&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Portrait of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sophie_Germain&quot;&gt;Sophie Germain&lt;/a&gt; (April 1, 1776 - June 27, 1831), &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Germain.jpeg&quot;&gt;[Public domain], via Wikimedia Commons&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alas, 173 is also an &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Odious_number&quot;&gt;odious number&lt;/a&gt;, which may sound rather bad but just means it has an odd number of 1&#39;s in binary (10101101).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that you&#39;ve warmed up, let us once again enter the decidely wonderful, balanced madness of the mathematical blogging carnival.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Likely most people (or at least the most people) will already have seen the NYT&#39;s Kenneth Chang looking into &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2019/08/06/science/math-equation-pemdas.html&quot;&gt;Why Mathematicians hate that viral equation&lt;/a&gt;; but really who needs 8÷2(2+2) when you can so easily have drama with the Oxford Comma.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any case, make sure you head over to Over at the Art of Research where Vi Hart shared &lt;a href=&quot;https://theartofresearch.org/computation-for-hands-systems-for-humans/&quot;&gt;Computation for Hands, Systems for Humans&lt;/a&gt;, taking you on the magic carpet ride that&#39;s Vi&#39;s hands &amp;quot;craving computation&amp;quot;, combining hardware, software, systems thinking, VR and a ton of other ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before you continue to Ari Rubinsztejn explains &lt;a href=&quot;https://gereshes.com/2019/05/27/why-tracking-space-debris-is-so-hard/&quot;&gt;Why Tracking Space Debris is so Hard&lt;/a&gt; (thanks, nonlinear dynamics!), step under the cover of the Undercover economist Tim Harford who wrote on &lt;a href=&quot;http://timharford.com/2019/08/the-strange-power-of-the-idea-of-average/&quot;&gt;the strange power of the idea of average&lt;/a&gt;, both good and bad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course any mathematically topic is worth a deep dive into, so head into the magical depths of the Math Vault for an extensive article on &lt;a href=&quot;https://mathvault.ca/long-division/&quot;&gt;Long Division and Its Variants (for Integers)&lt;/a&gt; Once you&#39;re ready, jump out and get yourself back into Cantor&#39;s Paradise where Jørgen Veisdal will let you in on &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/cantors-paradise/the-mathematics-of-elo-ratings-b6bfc9ca1dba&quot;&gt;the mathematics of Elo ratings&lt;/a&gt;, a glimpse at the history of the famous ranking system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before you lose your king or queen, let Richard Elwes ask you a question befit Carol&#39;s Red Queen: &lt;a href=&quot;https://richardelwes.co.uk/2019/09/06/how-many-sides-does-a-circle-have/&quot;&gt;How Many Sides Does A Circle Have?&lt;/a&gt; and be sure to follow him off on a tanget or two. If all those tangents twirled you around too much, switch to a classical, sold blog post by the amazing John Cook who will help you &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.johndcook.com/blog/2019/08/27/heaps-law/&quot;&gt;estimate vocabulary size with Heaps’ law&lt;/a&gt; just in case you need to verify a post-humously discovered manuscript by Jane Austen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To ease your way out of those particular mazes, take a sip and mingle over at &lt;a href=&quot;https://ima.org.uk/12133/editorial-august-2019/&quot;&gt;this month&#39;s IMA editorial&lt;/a&gt;, if only to catch up on the Queen’s Birthday Honours List for 2019. And if you are one of those people who frequent the always dramatic birdsite, here are a two math-focused threads for you:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Oh no, I&amp;#39;ve deliberately obscured large portions of this ruler and I need to make sure these vegetables are whole numbers of inches long or my toddler will eat me instead: a &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/RealWorldMaths?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#RealWorldMaths&lt;/a&gt; thread &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/GWuZMry6Ti&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/GWuZMry6Ti&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Christian Lawson-Perfect (@christianp) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/christianp/status/1169651584416079872?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;September 5, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Unpopular take: As someone with a Master&amp;#39;s degree in statistics and who teaches data science, I&amp;#39;m very much over the &amp;quot;data scientists are incompetent fools who just throw data in and get results from a computer with no critical thinking&amp;quot; takes. 1/&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Matt Brems (@matthewbrems) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/matthewbrems/status/1163224585644511233?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;August 18, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/mathyawp/status/1162462128441139201?s=19&quot;&gt;Also via twitter&lt;/a&gt;, Francis Su shared his handout with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.math.hmc.edu/~su/math131/good-math-writing.pdf&quot;&gt;Guildelines for good mathematical writing (PDF)&lt;/a&gt; which he says you should feel free to share with your students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To wrap things up, take a carousel of math blogging perfection at Math Off The Grid where Benjamin Leis&#39;s post on &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.mathoffthegrid.com/2019/08/cardanos-method.html&quot;&gt;Cardano&#39;s Method&lt;/a&gt; starts from a new video from Mathologer (below), picks up &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/MrHonner/status/1165417359764533248?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;a tweet by Patrick Honner&lt;/a&gt; throws in &lt;a href=&quot;https://artofproblemsolving.com/news/aftermath/aftermath-running-a-school-for-math-lovers-with-sam-vandervelde&quot;&gt;a podcast with Sam Vandervelde&lt;/a&gt; and tops it off with a pointer to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marden%27s_theorem&quot;&gt;Marden&#39;s Theorem&lt;/a&gt; to drag you into the carnival that is Wikipedia&#39;s mathematics articles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;style&gt;.embed-container { position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden; max-width: 100%; } .embed-container iframe, .embed-container object, .embed-container embed { position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; }&lt;/style&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;embed-container&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/QILiHiTD3uc&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s it for the beautiful month of September. Thanks to everyone who submitted a post! After almost 9 years of running&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Be sure to stop by next month’s Carnival. You should &lt;a href=&quot;http://aperiodical.com/carnival-of-mathematics/&quot;&gt;submit your favorite blog posts/videos/content&lt;/a&gt; from the month of September. If you’d like to host an upcoming show, please get in touch with &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:katie@aperiodical.com&quot;&gt;Katie&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>Weeknote 2019/37</title>
		<link href="https://www.peterkrautzberger.org/0211/"/>
		<updated>2019-09-13T22:00:00+02:00</updated>
		<id>https://www.peterkrautzberger.org/0211/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve fallen silent this year. There were a lot of reasons for that. Mostly bad things, but many good things, too. I want to try to find a way back to writing, especially given this blog&#39;s 10&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; anniversary coming up in December. I&#39;ve never been very personal on this personal site of mine; or perhaps more precisely I may not have appeared to be so, that is, I&#39;ve not been writing the stuff most people think of when they say &amp;quot;personal website&amp;quot;. I&#39;m thinking maybe I&#39;ll give it a try.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway. I really like this idea of a weeknote which I first saw at &lt;a href=&quot;https://daverupert.com/&quot;&gt;Dave Rupert&#39;s&lt;/a&gt; and then at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.baldurbjarnason.com/&quot;&gt;Baldur Bjarnason&#39;s&lt;/a&gt;. Let&#39;s give it a try and see how it feels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Work&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Work has been mixed this week. A big chunk of in-depth work was finalizing (what feels like a countless number of) tests for a very old piece of code that never had any tests. As this code had grown into a little bit of a monster, I now feel much more in control of it and ready to rewrite/port it. I also got into the GitHub Actions beta this week which looks nice and should help automate a bunch of stuff that&#39;s being done by a much less natural GitHub app (client permitting, anyway).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh, and I had some interesting work helping some (print) designers wrap their heads around some web thing. That was a ton of fun and maybe it will turn into more, we&#39;ll see.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reading&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve been having a fit of escapism and churning through Harry Dresden novels at a high pace; as re-readings go, these are still quite good. I still don&#39;t like some things but I do still like how he grew the universe, something so many fantasy series fail at. This year really has been a year of re-reading incidentally; there are worse things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Life&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had the yearly meeting of our daycare (which is set up as an association run by the parents). I&#39;m the data privacy person for another year which has really been quite interesting (thanks, GDPR); after focusing on the digital side (where I&#39;m more comfortable), it&#39;s time to focus on the physical side, where I look forward to learning a few new things. Otherwise, I was amazed how little drama we had; in the end, we seem to be good people, wanting to make things better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://scoskey.org/&quot;&gt;Sam&lt;/a&gt; and I are back to regular meetings after a long summer which is just plain good. Besides good times, we are working on upgrades to &lt;a href=&quot;http://mathblogging.org/&quot;&gt;mathblogging.org&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://boolesrings.org/&quot;&gt;boolesrings.org&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also think it may be time to finally fix my laptop&#39;s keyboard. First the left ctrl key went (which was fun to relearn with the right ctrl key), then the tick and some numbers started to become iffy (which gets annoying) but with the letter E starting to act up I&#39;m really coming to the end of the line. I don&#39;t know why I keep dragging it out. Let&#39;s see if I have an update in the next note, shall we?&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>Weeknote 2019/38</title>
		<link href="https://www.peterkrautzberger.org/0212/"/>
		<updated>2019-09-20T22:00:00+02:00</updated>
		<id>https://www.peterkrautzberger.org/0212/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Let&#39;s see if I can &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.peterkrautzberger.org/0211&quot;&gt;keep this up&lt;/a&gt;. I have a feeling these posts could be a collection of all the small bits and pieces that do not warrant a blog post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Work&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Work was full of organizational stuff - everything from reorganizing git repos to organizing people to organizing reporting data. So in many ways uneventful but for me usually a form of complementary exercise which gives me a productivity boost once all the end-of-quarter shenanigans are over.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Media&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve been thinking about my media usage recently, in particular the role of podcasts and video hosting platforms (ok, mostly youtube at the moment).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the past two decades, the internet gradually eliminated any need (of mine) for TV consumption. Besides the obvious (there&#39;s a ton of media with a single subscription to a streaming service, a ton more with multiple subscriptions, and virtually all media in gray areas), I was pondering &amp;quot;TV programming&amp;quot; recently. It&#39;s something that many friends still describe as pleasing (switch on the TV and just watch something) and I would usually argue against it which seems odd since I was fairly addicted to it as a kid/ya. But recently I noticed how similar subscriptions to YouTube channels work. This is especially impressive with more original work such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Druck_(Webserie)&quot;&gt;Druck&lt;/a&gt;, the German version of &lt;a href=&quot;https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Skam_(Fernsehserie)&quot;&gt;Skam&lt;/a&gt;, which timestamps its episodes and releases them on matching times of day. Reading about their approach (and watching a season, which was quite interesting in itself and as a parent) made me realize how I use my YouTube subscriptions like TV programming. It&#39;s ephemeral, passing me by, tuning in, maybe hopping to the next one. And yet it&#39;s way better than even tivo-era TV as it gives both the ephemeral and the archival.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similarly, podcasts (and again to some degree YouTube) have done much of the same for my radio consumption. Serious news stations like Deutschlandfunk, BBC 4, and various forms of NPR have been in my life since forever, and yet their consumption has been reduced to morning news and otherwise podcasts. In addition, podcasting covers anything from web industry to fiction, from comedy to whatever &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.richter.fm/category/podcast/derweisheit&quot;&gt;Der Weisheit&lt;/a&gt; is (basically 4 friends chatting). I struggled to find interesting music podcasts (as in: playing contemporary popular music) for a while but I eventually found a few I liked; YouTube music channels do the rest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyhoo, just a reminder that this internet is wonderful, I guess.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I thought one way to use this format might be to just browse through Mastodon and see what I find (boosted or, gasp, original content). So here we go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Christian posted lovely 3D printable Lᵖ norm balls thing:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://mathstodon.xyz/@christianp/102807944228401858/embed&quot; class=&quot;mastodon-embed&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 100%; border: 0&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;allowfullscreen&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://mathstodon.xyz/@christianp/102807949209412600/embed&quot; class=&quot;mastodon-embed&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 100%; border: 0&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;allowfullscreen&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;David Eppstein linked to a glorious collection of Turing Complete things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/102789724968251958/embed&quot; class=&quot;mastodon-embed&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 100%; border: 0&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;allowfullscreen&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://mathstodon.xyz/embed.js&quot; async=&quot;async&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Life&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We finally went to &lt;a href=&quot;https://fridaysforfuture.de/allefuersklima/&quot;&gt;fridays for future&lt;/a&gt; this week; the fucking least we can all do is to show up whenever we can and always support them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh, my keyboard; I wanted to get onto that, didn&#39;t I.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>Using grid to split a table cell</title>
		<link href="https://www.peterkrautzberger.org/0213/"/>
		<updated>2019-12-30T23:00:00+01:00</updated>
		<id>https://www.peterkrautzberger.org/0213/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Well that kind of a break sucked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other day I got to think about a little problem: split table cells.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.peterkrautzberger.org/assets/2019/splitcell.png&quot; alt=&quot;a table with first cell containing column and header information, separated by a diagonal line&quot;&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Source &lt;a href=&quot;https://tex.stackexchange.com/q/89745&quot;&gt;tex.SE&lt;/a&gt;, CC-by-SA 4.0 &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you search around the web for CSS solutions,&lt;br&gt;
you&#39;ll mostly find more or less fiddly ones: &lt;a href=&quot;https://stackoverflow.com/questions/45506550/how-can-a-split-diagonally-a-table-header-cell&quot;&gt;this one from StackOverflow&lt;/a&gt; hacks a border by transforming it - awesome hackery. I also liked &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Template:Diagonal_split_header&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&#39;s solution&lt;/a&gt;, which takes a standard strike-through using gradients and automatically calculates the specific values for margins to keep the &amp;quot;sub cells&amp;quot; from the diagonal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I was thinking that we should be able to do better these days. Shouldn&#39;t we get to stop worrying about the dimensions of the content?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Grid to the rescue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;style style=&quot;display: block; white-space: pre-wrap; margin-bottom: 1em;&quot;&gt;
.cell {
  display: grid;
  width: max-content;
  justify-content: space-between;
  grid-template-columns: repeat(2, 1fr);
  grid-auto-rows: 1fr;
  border: 1px solid #000;
  background: url(&quot;data:image/svg+xml;utf8,&lt;svg xmlns=&#39;http://www.w3.org/2000/svg&#39; version=&#39;1.1&#39; preserveAspectRatio=&#39;none&#39; viewBox=&#39;0 0 100 100&#39;&gt;&lt;line x1=&#39;0&#39; y1=&#39;0&#39; x2=&#39;100&#39; y2=&#39;100&#39; stroke=&#39;black&#39; vector-effect=&#39;non-scaling-stroke&#39;/&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&quot;);
  background-size: 100% 100%;
  margin-bottom: 1rem;
}

.cell--topRight {
  grid-column-start: 2;
  text-align: right;
}

.cell--bottomLeft {
  grid-column-start: 1;
}
&lt;/style&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;cell diag&quot; contenteditable=&quot;true&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;cell--topRight&quot;&gt;Top and Right&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;cell--bottomLeft&quot;&gt;Bottom and Left&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A simple 2x2 grid an inlined background SVG to draw the diagonal; column placement creates faux cells alongside auto-rows at 1fr ensure we don&#39;t cross the line. In other words, an (almost) content-agnostic split table cell.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can go ahead and edit the text to try it out. See if you can find some edge cases where it fails (and let me know if you find a real case).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And in real life don&#39;t forget to add some non-visual hints to clarify which part is which, especially in a table head.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Happy New Year.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>Tech update</title>
		<link href="https://www.peterkrautzberger.org/0214/"/>
		<updated>2020-10-06T22:00:00+02:00</updated>
		<id>https://www.peterkrautzberger.org/0214/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This site is nearing its 11th anniversary and the past year has not been kind to my writing around here. I can&#39;t even say there are a lot of drafts or some such, just a lot of emptiness after lots of hours in ICU waiting rooms and then straight into covid19.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve been trying to get back to writing here and as these things tend to go, it took spare time over a few months to upgrade the underlying tech instead. A large part of this was playing around with MathJax, which migh seem somewhat silly since I don&#39;t write mathematics much anymore. However, I use MathJax a lot for work and it was time to implement a few things I had wanted to dogfood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The basics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/pkra/peterkrautzberger.org/commit/dad56ad9e9e8efd21486cd4345a7a6b652f48c1c&quot;&gt;Two years ago&lt;/a&gt;, I switched from &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com/&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt; (to which I had at some point added a &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/pkra/peterkrautzberger.org/commit/2be9697f9fc4900da285eac705e5cca1785ccac9&quot;&gt;travis build&lt;/a&gt; to run &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mathjax/MathJax-node&quot;&gt;mathjax-node&lt;/a&gt;) to &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/11ty/eleventy&quot;&gt;eleventy&lt;/a&gt;. The primary reason was that I wanted more control over my build and since I work primarily with (vanilla) JavaScript, eleventy was (and continues to be) a very good choice. But I didn&#39;t find time to work out a proper integration of mathjax-node so I went back to client-side MathJax (naturally with its accessibility extension active by default).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So obviously I upgraded eleventy which went as smooth as can be - just some minor plugin changes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;the new stuff&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The step back to client-side MathJax was supposed to get me two steps forward towards testing my new tech here. But shit hit the fan and here we are two years later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.peterkrautzberger.org/209/&quot;&gt;my last significant piece of writing around here&lt;/a&gt;, I&#39;ve been continuing to work on accessible and explorable server-side MathJax rendering (and beyond that more generally &amp;quot;complex&amp;quot; content). I favor MathJax&#39;s SVG output for both technical and philosophical reasons but a key problem for the (now retired) &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/krautzource/mathjax-sre-walker/&quot;&gt;mathjax-sre-walker&lt;/a&gt; had been that MathJax v2 dropped some internal structure in its SVG output (to get smaller SVGs), which in particular meant that any table construction failed to become explorable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So really rolling out these exploration ideas meant upgrading to MathJax v3 - which was a bit of a pain, to be honest. I have many (many) feelings about MathJax v3 and should do a post on it at some point. But for now let&#39;s just say that I ran into many small bugs, some fixed but not released, others not yet fixed when I found them. All in all, maybe a dozen bugs that just dragged things out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the same time, my exploration tooling continued to evolve and mathjax-sre-walker has now been retired in favor of &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/krautzource/aria-tree-walker&quot;&gt;aria-tree-walker&lt;/a&gt; as well as &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/krautzource/sre-to-tree/&quot;&gt;sre-to-tree&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aria-tree-walker is a tiny (&amp;lt;1kb zipped) walker for ARIA trees with a fairly specific markup structure: the tree is marked up via aria-owns and each tree item is named by an aria-label. Sre-to-tree translates SRE&#39;s structural information to just such a suitable tree. Rolling out the walker led to me finding several minor bugs found in &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/zorkow/speech-rule-engine/&quot;&gt;speech-rule-engine&lt;/a&gt;, thus more delay. (But don&#39;t get me wrong, Davide and Volker have been super responsive as always when it came to these bugs.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So 3-4 moving pieces for equations, lots of bugs, lots of growing pains. Fun stuff really and the main point why I wanted to test these technologies here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;markdown&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The third part was to integrate these moving pieces back into eleventy. Fortunately, I found an existing markdown+mathjax plugin that was designed to not just ignore TeX content but render it server-side. Unfortunately, &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/tani/markdown-it-mathjax3&quot;&gt;markdown-it-mathjax3&lt;/a&gt; wasn&#39;t quite flexible enough to let me do my thing. But it helped me solve a major problem: hooking into markdown(-it) processing. So &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/pkra/peterkrautzberger.org/blob/e30b9db2761482b57fc9c6f414d41f331bcdd05d/markdown-it-mathjax3-hacked.js&quot;&gt;I forked it&lt;/a&gt; to hook into &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/pkra/peterkrautzberger.org/blob/e30b9db2761482b57fc9c6f414d41f331bcdd05d/tex2svg-tree.js&quot;&gt;my custom MathJax v3 setup&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a side effect, a ton of markdown content broke because markdown-it-mathjax follows pandoc&#39;s TeX-in-markdown rules and my old writing didn&#39;t adhere to that. Which took me through a fun romp of my content, &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/pkra/peterkrautzberger.org/commit/f3a73f7c713610938a07fc11faaa04229294895c&quot;&gt;fixing lots of stuff&lt;/a&gt;, including more errors from previous rewrites (embarassing) and also bugs in the tooling (awesome). Some posts hold up rather well, others not so much; I should maybe write about that some time (ahaha, listen to yourself, man).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, some CSS and JS updates were in order: adding the aria-tree-walker when necessary and styling the exploration - which led to yet more bug reports (yay). After &lt;a href=&quot;https://mathstodon.xyz/@pkra/104970592018504650&quot;&gt;teasing myself on mathstodon&lt;/a&gt; I was finally ready to push it out last week. In the end, the setup isn&#39;t the most efficient but it&#39;s ok for now; a 1 min build time is bareable and yet probably enough pressure to optimize later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Coda&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No next steps as life gets in the way too much these days. Ping me if you have any questions on the setup. For good measure, here&#39;s an equation which should - final piece - also render in the atom/rss feed (though exploration will probably fail as most feed readers won&#39;t run JavaScript). &lt;a href=&quot;https://krautzource.github.io/aria-tree-walker/&quot;&gt;As described in the aria-tree-walker docs&lt;/a&gt; AT users will get the full text in browse mode but can switch to focus mode to explore with arrow keys; visual users can focus the equation (e.g., tab to it or left-click it) and then explore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;mjx-container class=&quot;MathJax&quot; jax=&quot;SVG&quot; display=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;svg style=&quot;vertical-align: -2.827ex;&quot; xmlns=&quot;http://www.w3.org/2000/svg&quot; width=&quot;29.215ex&quot; height=&quot;6.785ex&quot; role=&quot;treeitem&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 -1749.5 12913.1 2999&quot; xmlns:xlink=&quot;http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink&quot; tabindex=&quot;0&quot; data-treewalker=&quot;&quot; aria-owns=&quot;MJX-0a687506f2d0a0fc4cf9693b366040a2-36 MJX-0a687506f2d0a0fc4cf9693b366040a2-12 MJX-0a687506f2d0a0fc4cf9693b366040a2-33&quot; aria-label=&quot;upper F upper S left parenthesis x Subscript i Baseline right parenthesis Subscript i element of omega Baseline equals StartSet sigma summation Underscript k element of s Endscripts x Subscript k Baseline vertical bar s subset of or equal to Subscript f Baseline omega EndSet&quot;&gt;&lt;defs&gt;&lt;path id=&quot;MJX-2447-TEX-N-46&quot; d=&quot;M128 619Q121 626 117 628T101 631T58 634H25V680H582V676Q584 670 596 560T610 444V440H570V444Q563 493 561 501Q555 538 543 563T516 601T477 622T431 631T374 633H334H286Q252 633 244 631T233 621Q232 619 232 490V363H284Q287 363 303 363T327 364T349 367T372 373T389 385Q407 403 410 459V480H450V200H410V221Q407 276 389 296Q381 303 371 307T348 313T327 316T303 317T284 317H232V189L233 61Q240 54 245 52T270 48T333 46H360V0H348Q324 3 182 3Q51 3 36 0H25V46H58Q100 47 109 49T128 61V619Z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;path id=&quot;MJX-2447-TEX-N-53&quot; d=&quot;M55 507Q55 590 112 647T243 704H257Q342 704 405 641L426 672Q431 679 436 687T446 700L449 704Q450 704 453 704T459 705H463Q466 705 472 699V462L466 456H448Q437 456 435 459T430 479Q413 605 329 646Q292 662 254 662Q201 662 168 626T135 542Q135 508 152 480T200 435Q210 431 286 412T370 389Q427 367 463 314T500 191Q500 110 448 45T301 -21Q245 -21 201 -4T140 27L122 41Q118 36 107 21T87 -7T78 -21Q76 -22 68 -22H64Q61 -22 55 -16V101Q55 220 56 222Q58 227 76 227H89Q95 221 95 214Q95 182 105 151T139 90T205 42T305 24Q352 24 386 62T420 155Q420 198 398 233T340 281Q284 295 266 300Q261 301 239 306T206 314T174 325T141 343T112 367T85 402Q55 451 55 507Z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;path id=&quot;MJX-2447-TEX-N-2061&quot; d=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;path id=&quot;MJX-2447-TEX-N-28&quot; d=&quot;M94 250Q94 319 104 381T127 488T164 576T202 643T244 695T277 729T302 750H315H319Q333 750 333 741Q333 738 316 720T275 667T226 581T184 443T167 250T184 58T225 -81T274 -167T316 -220T333 -241Q333 -250 318 -250H315H302L274 -226Q180 -141 137 -14T94 250Z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;path id=&quot;MJX-2447-TEX-I-1D465&quot; d=&quot;M52 289Q59 331 106 386T222 442Q257 442 286 424T329 379Q371 442 430 442Q467 442 494 420T522 361Q522 332 508 314T481 292T458 288Q439 288 427 299T415 328Q415 374 465 391Q454 404 425 404Q412 404 406 402Q368 386 350 336Q290 115 290 78Q290 50 306 38T341 26Q378 26 414 59T463 140Q466 150 469 151T485 153H489Q504 153 504 145Q504 144 502 134Q486 77 440 33T333 -11Q263 -11 227 52Q186 -10 133 -10H127Q78 -10 57 16T35 71Q35 103 54 123T99 143Q142 143 142 101Q142 81 130 66T107 46T94 41L91 40Q91 39 97 36T113 29T132 26Q168 26 194 71Q203 87 217 139T245 247T261 313Q266 340 266 352Q266 380 251 392T217 404Q177 404 142 372T93 290Q91 281 88 280T72 278H58Q52 284 52 289Z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;path id=&quot;MJX-2447-TEX-I-1D456&quot; d=&quot;M184 600Q184 624 203 642T247 661Q265 661 277 649T290 619Q290 596 270 577T226 557Q211 557 198 567T184 600ZM21 287Q21 295 30 318T54 369T98 420T158 442Q197 442 223 419T250 357Q250 340 236 301T196 196T154 83Q149 61 149 51Q149 26 166 26Q175 26 185 29T208 43T235 78T260 137Q263 149 265 151T282 153Q302 153 302 143Q302 135 293 112T268 61T223 11T161 -11Q129 -11 102 10T74 74Q74 91 79 106T122 220Q160 321 166 341T173 380Q173 404 156 404H154Q124 404 99 371T61 287Q60 286 59 284T58 281T56 279T53 278T49 278T41 278H27Q21 284 21 287Z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;path id=&quot;MJX-2447-TEX-N-29&quot; d=&quot;M60 749L64 750Q69 750 74 750H86L114 726Q208 641 251 514T294 250Q294 182 284 119T261 12T224 -76T186 -143T145 -194T113 -227T90 -246Q87 -249 86 -250H74Q66 -250 63 -250T58 -247T55 -238Q56 -237 66 -225Q221 -64 221 250T66 725Q56 737 55 738Q55 746 60 749Z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;path id=&quot;MJX-2447-TEX-N-2208&quot; d=&quot;M84 250Q84 372 166 450T360 539Q361 539 377 539T419 540T469 540H568Q583 532 583 520Q583 511 570 501L466 500Q355 499 329 494Q280 482 242 458T183 409T147 354T129 306T124 272V270H568Q583 262 583 250T568 230H124V228Q124 207 134 177T167 112T231 48T328 7Q355 1 466 0H570Q583 -10 583 -20Q583 -32 568 -40H471Q464 -40 446 -40T417 -41Q262 -41 172 45Q84 127 84 250Z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;path id=&quot;MJX-2447-TEX-I-1D714&quot; d=&quot;M495 384Q495 406 514 424T555 443Q574 443 589 425T604 364Q604 334 592 278T555 155T483 38T377 -11Q297 -11 267 66Q266 68 260 61Q201 -11 125 -11Q15 -11 15 139Q15 230 56 325T123 434Q135 441 147 436Q160 429 160 418Q160 406 140 379T94 306T62 208Q61 202 61 187Q61 124 85 100T143 76Q201 76 245 129L253 137V156Q258 297 317 297Q348 297 348 261Q348 243 338 213T318 158L308 135Q309 133 310 129T318 115T334 97T358 83T393 76Q456 76 501 148T546 274Q546 305 533 325T508 357T495 384Z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;path id=&quot;MJX-2447-TEX-N-3D&quot; d=&quot;M56 347Q56 360 70 367H707Q722 359 722 347Q722 336 708 328L390 327H72Q56 332 56 347ZM56 153Q56 168 72 173H708Q722 163 722 153Q722 140 707 133H70Q56 140 56 153Z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;path id=&quot;MJX-2447-TEX-S4-7B&quot; d=&quot;M661 -1243L655 -1249H622L604 -1240Q503 -1190 434 -1107T348 -909Q346 -897 346 -499L345 -98L343 -82Q335 3 287 87T157 223Q146 232 145 236Q144 240 144 250Q144 265 145 268T157 278Q242 333 288 417T343 583L345 600L346 1001Q346 1398 348 1410Q379 1622 600 1739L622 1750H655L661 1744V1727V1721Q661 1712 661 1710T657 1705T648 1700T630 1690T602 1668Q589 1659 574 1643T531 1593T484 1508T459 1398Q458 1389 458 1001Q458 614 457 605Q441 435 301 316Q254 277 202 251L250 222Q260 216 301 185Q443 66 457 -104Q458 -113 458 -501Q458 -888 459 -897Q463 -944 478 -988T509 -1060T548 -1114T580 -1149T602 -1167Q620 -1183 634 -1192T653 -1202T659 -1207T661 -1220V-1226V-1243Z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;path id=&quot;MJX-2447-TEX-LO-2211&quot; d=&quot;M60 948Q63 950 665 950H1267L1325 815Q1384 677 1388 669H1348L1341 683Q1320 724 1285 761Q1235 809 1174 838T1033 881T882 898T699 902H574H543H251L259 891Q722 258 724 252Q725 250 724 246Q721 243 460 -56L196 -356Q196 -357 407 -357Q459 -357 548 -357T676 -358Q812 -358 896 -353T1063 -332T1204 -283T1307 -196Q1328 -170 1348 -124H1388Q1388 -125 1381 -145T1356 -210T1325 -294L1267 -449L666 -450Q64 -450 61 -448Q55 -446 55 -439Q55 -437 57 -433L590 177Q590 178 557 222T452 366T322 544L56 909L55 924Q55 945 60 948Z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;path id=&quot;MJX-2447-TEX-I-1D458&quot; d=&quot;M121 647Q121 657 125 670T137 683Q138 683 209 688T282 694Q294 694 294 686Q294 679 244 477Q194 279 194 272Q213 282 223 291Q247 309 292 354T362 415Q402 442 438 442Q468 442 485 423T503 369Q503 344 496 327T477 302T456 291T438 288Q418 288 406 299T394 328Q394 353 410 369T442 390L458 393Q446 405 434 405H430Q398 402 367 380T294 316T228 255Q230 254 243 252T267 246T293 238T320 224T342 206T359 180T365 147Q365 130 360 106T354 66Q354 26 381 26Q429 26 459 145Q461 153 479 153H483Q499 153 499 144Q499 139 496 130Q455 -11 378 -11Q333 -11 305 15T277 90Q277 108 280 121T283 145Q283 167 269 183T234 206T200 217T182 220H180Q168 178 159 139T145 81T136 44T129 20T122 7T111 -2Q98 -11 83 -11Q66 -11 57 -1T48 16Q48 26 85 176T158 471L195 616Q196 629 188 632T149 637H144Q134 637 131 637T124 640T121 647Z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;path id=&quot;MJX-2447-TEX-I-1D460&quot; d=&quot;M131 289Q131 321 147 354T203 415T300 442Q362 442 390 415T419 355Q419 323 402 308T364 292Q351 292 340 300T328 326Q328 342 337 354T354 372T367 378Q368 378 368 379Q368 382 361 388T336 399T297 405Q249 405 227 379T204 326Q204 301 223 291T278 274T330 259Q396 230 396 163Q396 135 385 107T352 51T289 7T195 -10Q118 -10 86 19T53 87Q53 126 74 143T118 160Q133 160 146 151T160 120Q160 94 142 76T111 58Q109 57 108 57T107 55Q108 52 115 47T146 34T201 27Q237 27 263 38T301 66T318 97T323 122Q323 150 302 164T254 181T195 196T148 231Q131 256 131 289Z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;path id=&quot;MJX-2447-TEX-N-7C&quot; d=&quot;M139 -249H137Q125 -249 119 -235V251L120 737Q130 750 139 750Q152 750 159 735V-235Q151 -249 141 -249H139Z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;path id=&quot;MJX-2447-TEX-N-2286&quot; d=&quot;M84 346Q84 468 166 546T360 635Q361 635 370 635T395 635T430 636T475 636T524 636H679Q694 628 694 616Q694 607 681 597L522 596H470H441Q366 596 338 592T266 568Q244 557 224 542T179 500T139 433T124 346V341Q124 253 185 185Q244 121 328 103Q348 98 366 98T522 96H681Q694 86 694 76Q694 64 679 56H526Q510 56 480 56T434 55Q350 55 289 71T172 141Q84 223 84 346ZM104 -131T104 -118T118 -98H679Q694 -106 694 -118T679 -138H118Q104 -131 104 -118Z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;path id=&quot;MJX-2447-TEX-I-1D453&quot; d=&quot;M118 -162Q120 -162 124 -164T135 -167T147 -168Q160 -168 171 -155T187 -126Q197 -99 221 27T267 267T289 382V385H242Q195 385 192 387Q188 390 188 397L195 425Q197 430 203 430T250 431Q298 431 298 432Q298 434 307 482T319 540Q356 705 465 705Q502 703 526 683T550 630Q550 594 529 578T487 561Q443 561 443 603Q443 622 454 636T478 657L487 662Q471 668 457 668Q445 668 434 658T419 630Q412 601 403 552T387 469T380 433Q380 431 435 431Q480 431 487 430T498 424Q499 420 496 407T491 391Q489 386 482 386T428 385H372L349 263Q301 15 282 -47Q255 -132 212 -173Q175 -205 139 -205Q107 -205 81 -186T55 -132Q55 -95 76 -78T118 -61Q162 -61 162 -103Q162 -122 151 -136T127 -157L118 -162Z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;path id=&quot;MJX-2447-TEX-S4-7D&quot; d=&quot;M144 1727Q144 1743 146 1746T162 1750H167H183L203 1740Q274 1705 325 1658T403 1562T440 1478T456 1410Q458 1398 458 1001Q459 661 459 624T465 558Q470 526 480 496T502 441T529 395T559 356T588 325T615 301T637 284T654 273L660 269V266Q660 263 660 259T661 250V239Q661 236 661 234T660 232T656 229T649 224Q577 179 528 105T465 -57Q460 -86 460 -123T458 -499V-661Q458 -857 457 -893T447 -955Q425 -1048 359 -1120T203 -1239L183 -1249H168Q150 -1249 147 -1246T144 -1226Q144 -1213 145 -1210T153 -1202Q169 -1193 186 -1181T232 -1140T282 -1081T322 -1000T345 -897Q346 -888 346 -501Q346 -113 347 -104Q359 58 503 184Q554 226 603 250Q504 299 430 393T347 605Q346 614 346 1002Q346 1389 345 1398Q338 1493 288 1573T153 1703Q146 1707 145 1710T144 1727Z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/defs&gt;&lt;g stroke=&quot;currentColor&quot; fill=&quot;currentColor&quot; stroke-width=&quot;0&quot; transform=&quot;matrix(1 0 0 -1 0 0)&quot;&gt;&lt;g data-mml-node=&quot;math&quot; data-semantic-type=&quot;relseq&quot; data-semantic-role=&quot;equality&quot; data-semantic-id=&quot;37&quot; data-semantic-children=&quot;36,33&quot; data-semantic-content=&quot;12&quot; data-semantic-owns=&quot;36 12 33&quot; data-semantic-structure=&quot;(37 (36 0 35 (11 (34 2 (5 3 4) 6) (10 7 8 9))) 12 (33 13 (32 (30 (19 14 (18 15 16 17)) (22 20 21)) 23 (31 24 (27 25 26) 28)) 29))&quot; data-semantic-speech=&quot;upper F upper S left parenthesis x Subscript i Baseline right parenthesis Subscript i element of omega Baseline equals StartSet sigma summation Underscript k element of s Endscripts x Subscript k Baseline vertical bar s subset of or equal to Subscript f Baseline omega EndSet&quot; id=&quot;MJX-0a687506f2d0a0fc4cf9693b366040a2-37&quot;&gt;&lt;g data-mml-node=&quot;mrow&quot; data-semantic-type=&quot;appl&quot; data-semantic-role=&quot;simple function&quot; data-semantic-id=&quot;36&quot; data-semantic-children=&quot;0,11&quot; data-semantic-content=&quot;35,0&quot; data-semantic-parent=&quot;37&quot; data-semantic-owns=&quot;0 35 11&quot; data-semantic-speech=&quot;upper F upper S left parenthesis x Subscript i Baseline right parenthesis Subscript i element of omega Baseline&quot; id=&quot;MJX-0a687506f2d0a0fc4cf9693b366040a2-36&quot; aria-label=&quot;upper F upper S left parenthesis x Subscript i Baseline right parenthesis Subscript i element of omega Baseline&quot; role=&quot;treeitem&quot; aria-owns=&quot;MJX-0a687506f2d0a0fc4cf9693b366040a2-0 MJX-0a687506f2d0a0fc4cf9693b366040a2-35 MJX-0a687506f2d0a0fc4cf9693b366040a2-11&quot;&gt;&lt;g data-mml-node=&quot;mi&quot; data-semantic-type=&quot;identifier&quot; data-semantic-role=&quot;simple function&quot; data-semantic-font=&quot;normal&quot; data-semantic-annotation=&quot;clearspeak:simple;nemeth:number&quot; data-semantic-id=&quot;0&quot; data-semantic-parent=&quot;36&quot; data-semantic-operator=&quot;appl&quot; data-semantic-speech=&quot;upper F upper S&quot; id=&quot;MJX-0a687506f2d0a0fc4cf9693b366040a2-0&quot; aria-label=&quot;upper F upper S&quot; role=&quot;treeitem&quot;&gt;&lt;use xlink:href=&quot;#MJX-2447-TEX-N-46&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;&lt;/use&gt;&lt;use xlink:href=&quot;#MJX-2447-TEX-N-53&quot; transform=&quot;translate(653, 0)&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;&lt;/use&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;g data-mml-node=&quot;mo&quot; data-semantic-type=&quot;punctuation&quot; data-semantic-role=&quot;application&quot; data-semantic-id=&quot;35&quot; data-semantic-parent=&quot;36&quot; data-semantic-added=&quot;true&quot; data-semantic-operator=&quot;appl&quot; data-semantic-speech=&quot;of&quot; transform=&quot;translate(1209, 0)&quot; id=&quot;MJX-0a687506f2d0a0fc4cf9693b366040a2-35&quot; aria-label=&quot;of&quot; role=&quot;treeitem&quot;&gt;&lt;use xlink:href=&quot;#MJX-2447-TEX-N-2061&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;&lt;/use&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;g data-mml-node=&quot;msub&quot; data-semantic-type=&quot;subscript&quot; data-semantic-role=&quot;leftright&quot; data-semantic-fencepointer=&quot;6&quot; data-semantic-id=&quot;11&quot; data-semantic-children=&quot;34,10&quot; data-semantic-parent=&quot;36&quot; data-semantic-owns=&quot;34 10&quot; data-semantic-speech=&quot;left parenthesis x Subscript i Baseline right parenthesis Subscript i element of omega Baseline&quot; transform=&quot;translate(1375.7, 0)&quot; id=&quot;MJX-0a687506f2d0a0fc4cf9693b366040a2-11&quot; aria-label=&quot;left parenthesis x Subscript i Baseline right parenthesis Subscript i element of omega Baseline&quot; role=&quot;treeitem&quot; aria-owns=&quot;MJX-0a687506f2d0a0fc4cf9693b366040a2-34 MJX-0a687506f2d0a0fc4cf9693b366040a2-10&quot;&gt;&lt;g data-mml-node=&quot;mrow&quot; data-semantic-type=&quot;fenced&quot; data-semantic-role=&quot;leftright&quot; data-semantic-id=&quot;34&quot; data-semantic-children=&quot;5&quot; data-semantic-content=&quot;2,6&quot; data-semantic-parent=&quot;11&quot; data-semantic-owns=&quot;2 5 6&quot; data-semantic-speech=&quot;left parenthesis x Subscript i Baseline right parenthesis&quot; data-semantic-prefix=&quot;Base&quot; id=&quot;MJX-0a687506f2d0a0fc4cf9693b366040a2-34&quot; aria-label=&quot;Base left parenthesis x Subscript i Baseline right parenthesis&quot; role=&quot;treeitem&quot; aria-owns=&quot;MJX-0a687506f2d0a0fc4cf9693b366040a2-2 MJX-0a687506f2d0a0fc4cf9693b366040a2-5 MJX-0a687506f2d0a0fc4cf9693b366040a2-6&quot;&gt;&lt;g data-mml-node=&quot;mo&quot; data-semantic-type=&quot;fence&quot; data-semantic-role=&quot;open&quot; data-semantic-id=&quot;2&quot; data-semantic-parent=&quot;34&quot; data-semantic-speech=&quot;left parenthesis&quot; id=&quot;MJX-0a687506f2d0a0fc4cf9693b366040a2-2&quot; aria-label=&quot;left parenthesis&quot; role=&quot;treeitem&quot;&gt;&lt;use xlink:href=&quot;#MJX-2447-TEX-N-28&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;&lt;/use&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;g data-mml-node=&quot;msub&quot; data-semantic-type=&quot;subscript&quot; data-semantic-role=&quot;latinletter&quot; data-semantic-id=&quot;5&quot; data-semantic-children=&quot;3,4&quot; data-semantic-parent=&quot;34&quot; data-semantic-owns=&quot;3 4&quot; data-semantic-speech=&quot;x Subscript i Baseline&quot; transform=&quot;translate(389, 0)&quot; id=&quot;MJX-0a687506f2d0a0fc4cf9693b366040a2-5&quot; aria-label=&quot;x Subscript i Baseline&quot; role=&quot;treeitem&quot; aria-owns=&quot;MJX-0a687506f2d0a0fc4cf9693b366040a2-3 MJX-0a687506f2d0a0fc4cf9693b366040a2-4&quot;&gt;&lt;g data-mml-node=&quot;mi&quot; data-semantic-type=&quot;identifier&quot; data-semantic-role=&quot;latinletter&quot; data-semantic-font=&quot;italic&quot; data-semantic-annotation=&quot;clearspeak:simple;nemeth:number&quot; data-semantic-id=&quot;3&quot; data-semantic-parent=&quot;5&quot; data-semantic-speech=&quot;x&quot; data-semantic-prefix=&quot;Base&quot; id=&quot;MJX-0a687506f2d0a0fc4cf9693b366040a2-3&quot; aria-label=&quot;Base x&quot; role=&quot;treeitem&quot;&gt;&lt;use xlink:href=&quot;#MJX-2447-TEX-I-1D465&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;&lt;/use&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;g data-mml-node=&quot;mi&quot; transform=&quot;translate(572, -150) scale(0.707)&quot; data-semantic-type=&quot;identifier&quot; data-semantic-role=&quot;latinletter&quot; data-semantic-font=&quot;italic&quot; data-semantic-annotation=&quot;clearspeak:simple&quot; data-semantic-id=&quot;4&quot; data-semantic-parent=&quot;5&quot; data-semantic-speech=&quot;i&quot; data-semantic-prefix=&quot;Subscript&quot; id=&quot;MJX-0a687506f2d0a0fc4cf9693b366040a2-4&quot; aria-label=&quot;Subscript i&quot; role=&quot;treeitem&quot;&gt;&lt;use xlink:href=&quot;#MJX-2447-TEX-I-1D456&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;&lt;/use&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;g data-mml-node=&quot;mo&quot; data-semantic-type=&quot;fence&quot; data-semantic-role=&quot;close&quot; data-semantic-id=&quot;6&quot; data-semantic-parent=&quot;34&quot; data-semantic-speech=&quot;right parenthesis&quot; transform=&quot;translate(1255, 0)&quot; id=&quot;MJX-0a687506f2d0a0fc4cf9693b366040a2-6&quot; aria-label=&quot;right parenthesis&quot; role=&quot;treeitem&quot;&gt;&lt;use xlink:href=&quot;#MJX-2447-TEX-N-29&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;&lt;/use&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;g data-mml-node=&quot;mrow&quot; transform=&quot;translate(1644, -285.4) scale(0.707)&quot; data-semantic-type=&quot;infixop&quot; data-semantic-role=&quot;unknown&quot; data-semantic-id=&quot;10&quot; data-semantic-children=&quot;7,9&quot; data-semantic-content=&quot;8&quot; data-semantic-parent=&quot;11&quot; data-semantic-owns=&quot;7 8 9&quot; data-semantic-speech=&quot;i element of omega&quot; data-semantic-prefix=&quot;Subscript&quot; id=&quot;MJX-0a687506f2d0a0fc4cf9693b366040a2-10&quot; aria-label=&quot;Subscript i element of omega&quot; role=&quot;treeitem&quot; aria-owns=&quot;MJX-0a687506f2d0a0fc4cf9693b366040a2-7 MJX-0a687506f2d0a0fc4cf9693b366040a2-8 MJX-0a687506f2d0a0fc4cf9693b366040a2-9&quot;&gt;&lt;g data-mml-node=&quot;mi&quot; data-semantic-type=&quot;identifier&quot; data-semantic-role=&quot;latinletter&quot; data-semantic-font=&quot;italic&quot; data-semantic-annotation=&quot;clearspeak:simple&quot; data-semantic-id=&quot;7&quot; data-semantic-parent=&quot;10&quot; data-semantic-speech=&quot;i&quot; id=&quot;MJX-0a687506f2d0a0fc4cf9693b366040a2-7&quot; aria-label=&quot;i&quot; role=&quot;treeitem&quot;&gt;&lt;use xlink:href=&quot;#MJX-2447-TEX-I-1D456&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;&lt;/use&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;g data-mml-node=&quot;mo&quot; data-semantic-type=&quot;operator&quot; data-semantic-role=&quot;unknown&quot; data-semantic-id=&quot;8&quot; data-semantic-parent=&quot;10&quot; data-semantic-operator=&quot;infixop,∈&quot; data-semantic-speech=&quot;element of&quot; transform=&quot;translate(345, 0)&quot; id=&quot;MJX-0a687506f2d0a0fc4cf9693b366040a2-8&quot; aria-label=&quot;element of&quot; role=&quot;treeitem&quot;&gt;&lt;use xlink:href=&quot;#MJX-2447-TEX-N-2208&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;&lt;/use&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;g data-mml-node=&quot;mi&quot; data-semantic-type=&quot;identifier&quot; data-semantic-role=&quot;greekletter&quot; data-semantic-font=&quot;italic&quot; data-semantic-annotation=&quot;clearspeak:simple&quot; data-semantic-id=&quot;9&quot; data-semantic-parent=&quot;10&quot; data-semantic-speech=&quot;omega&quot; transform=&quot;translate(1012, 0)&quot; id=&quot;MJX-0a687506f2d0a0fc4cf9693b366040a2-9&quot; aria-label=&quot;omega&quot; role=&quot;treeitem&quot;&gt;&lt;use xlink:href=&quot;#MJX-2447-TEX-I-1D714&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;&lt;/use&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;g data-mml-node=&quot;mo&quot; data-semantic-type=&quot;relation&quot; data-semantic-role=&quot;equality&quot; data-semantic-id=&quot;12&quot; data-semantic-parent=&quot;37&quot; data-semantic-operator=&quot;relseq,=&quot; data-semantic-speech=&quot;equals&quot; transform=&quot;translate(4502.8, 0)&quot; id=&quot;MJX-0a687506f2d0a0fc4cf9693b366040a2-12&quot; aria-label=&quot;equals&quot; role=&quot;treeitem&quot;&gt;&lt;use xlink:href=&quot;#MJX-2447-TEX-N-3D&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;&lt;/use&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;g data-mml-node=&quot;TeXAtom&quot; data-semantic-type=&quot;fenced&quot; data-semantic-role=&quot;set extended&quot; data-semantic-id=&quot;33&quot; data-semantic-children=&quot;32&quot; data-semantic-content=&quot;13,29&quot; data-semantic-parent=&quot;37&quot; data-semantic-owns=&quot;13 32 29&quot; data-semantic-speech=&quot;StartSet sigma summation Underscript k element of s Endscripts x Subscript k Baseline vertical bar s subset of or equal to Subscript f Baseline omega EndSet&quot; data-mjx-texclass=&quot;INNER&quot; transform=&quot;translate(5558.6, 0)&quot; id=&quot;MJX-0a687506f2d0a0fc4cf9693b366040a2-33&quot; aria-label=&quot;StartSet sigma summation Underscript k element of s Endscripts x Subscript k Baseline vertical bar s subset of or equal to Subscript f Baseline omega EndSet&quot; role=&quot;treeitem&quot; aria-owns=&quot;MJX-0a687506f2d0a0fc4cf9693b366040a2-13 MJX-0a687506f2d0a0fc4cf9693b366040a2-32 MJX-0a687506f2d0a0fc4cf9693b366040a2-29&quot;&gt;&lt;g data-mml-node=&quot;mo&quot; data-semantic-type=&quot;fence&quot; data-semantic-role=&quot;open&quot; data-semantic-id=&quot;13&quot; data-semantic-parent=&quot;33&quot; data-semantic-operator=&quot;fenced&quot; data-semantic-speech=&quot;left brace&quot; id=&quot;MJX-0a687506f2d0a0fc4cf9693b366040a2-13&quot; aria-label=&quot;left brace&quot; role=&quot;treeitem&quot;&gt;&lt;use xlink:href=&quot;#MJX-2447-TEX-S4-7B&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;&lt;/use&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;g data-mml-node=&quot;mrow&quot; data-semantic-type=&quot;punctuated&quot; data-semantic-role=&quot;sequence&quot; data-semantic-id=&quot;32&quot; data-semantic-children=&quot;30,23,31&quot; data-semantic-content=&quot;23&quot; data-semantic-parent=&quot;33&quot; data-semantic-owns=&quot;30 23 31&quot; data-semantic-speech=&quot;sigma summation Underscript k element of s Endscripts x Subscript k Baseline vertical bar s subset of or equal to Subscript f Baseline omega&quot; transform=&quot;translate(806, 0)&quot; id=&quot;MJX-0a687506f2d0a0fc4cf9693b366040a2-32&quot; aria-label=&quot;sigma summation Underscript k element of s Endscripts x Subscript k Baseline vertical bar s subset of or equal to Subscript f Baseline omega&quot; role=&quot;treeitem&quot; aria-owns=&quot;MJX-0a687506f2d0a0fc4cf9693b366040a2-30 MJX-0a687506f2d0a0fc4cf9693b366040a2-23 MJX-0a687506f2d0a0fc4cf9693b366040a2-31&quot;&gt;&lt;g data-mml-node=&quot;mrow&quot; data-semantic-type=&quot;bigop&quot; data-semantic-role=&quot;sum&quot; data-semantic-id=&quot;30&quot; data-semantic-children=&quot;19,22&quot; data-semantic-content=&quot;14&quot; data-semantic-parent=&quot;32&quot; data-semantic-owns=&quot;19 22&quot; data-semantic-speech=&quot;sigma summation Underscript k element of s Endscripts x Subscript k Baseline&quot; id=&quot;MJX-0a687506f2d0a0fc4cf9693b366040a2-30&quot; aria-label=&quot;sigma summation Underscript k element of s Endscripts x Subscript k Baseline&quot; role=&quot;treeitem&quot; aria-owns=&quot;MJX-0a687506f2d0a0fc4cf9693b366040a2-19 MJX-0a687506f2d0a0fc4cf9693b366040a2-22&quot;&gt;&lt;g data-mml-node=&quot;munder&quot; data-semantic-type=&quot;limlower&quot; data-semantic-role=&quot;sum&quot; data-semantic-id=&quot;19&quot; data-semantic-children=&quot;14,18&quot; data-semantic-parent=&quot;30&quot; data-semantic-owns=&quot;14 18&quot; data-semantic-speech=&quot;sigma summation Underscript k element of s Endscripts&quot; id=&quot;MJX-0a687506f2d0a0fc4cf9693b366040a2-19&quot; aria-label=&quot;sigma summation Underscript k element of s Endscripts&quot; role=&quot;treeitem&quot; aria-owns=&quot;MJX-0a687506f2d0a0fc4cf9693b366040a2-14 MJX-0a687506f2d0a0fc4cf9693b366040a2-18&quot;&gt;&lt;g data-mml-node=&quot;mo&quot; data-semantic-type=&quot;largeop&quot; data-semantic-role=&quot;sum&quot; data-semantic-annotation=&quot;nemeth:number&quot; data-semantic-id=&quot;14&quot; data-semantic-parent=&quot;19&quot; data-semantic-operator=&quot;bigop&quot; data-semantic-speech=&quot;sigma summation&quot; id=&quot;MJX-0a687506f2d0a0fc4cf9693b366040a2-14&quot; aria-label=&quot;sigma summation&quot; role=&quot;treeitem&quot;&gt;&lt;use xlink:href=&quot;#MJX-2447-TEX-LO-2211&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;&lt;/use&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;g data-mml-node=&quot;mrow&quot; transform=&quot;translate(136.2, -1107.7) scale(0.707)&quot; data-semantic-type=&quot;infixop&quot; data-semantic-role=&quot;unknown&quot; data-semantic-id=&quot;18&quot; data-semantic-children=&quot;15,17&quot; data-semantic-content=&quot;16&quot; data-semantic-parent=&quot;19&quot; data-semantic-owns=&quot;15 16 17&quot; data-semantic-speech=&quot;k element of s&quot; id=&quot;MJX-0a687506f2d0a0fc4cf9693b366040a2-18&quot; aria-label=&quot;k element of s&quot; role=&quot;treeitem&quot; aria-owns=&quot;MJX-0a687506f2d0a0fc4cf9693b366040a2-15 MJX-0a687506f2d0a0fc4cf9693b366040a2-16 MJX-0a687506f2d0a0fc4cf9693b366040a2-17&quot;&gt;&lt;g data-mml-node=&quot;mi&quot; data-semantic-type=&quot;identifier&quot; data-semantic-role=&quot;latinletter&quot; data-semantic-font=&quot;italic&quot; data-semantic-annotation=&quot;clearspeak:simple&quot; data-semantic-id=&quot;15&quot; data-semantic-parent=&quot;18&quot; data-semantic-speech=&quot;k&quot; id=&quot;MJX-0a687506f2d0a0fc4cf9693b366040a2-15&quot; aria-label=&quot;k&quot; role=&quot;treeitem&quot;&gt;&lt;use xlink:href=&quot;#MJX-2447-TEX-I-1D458&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;&lt;/use&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;g data-mml-node=&quot;mo&quot; data-semantic-type=&quot;operator&quot; data-semantic-role=&quot;unknown&quot; data-semantic-id=&quot;16&quot; data-semantic-parent=&quot;18&quot; data-semantic-operator=&quot;infixop,∈&quot; data-semantic-speech=&quot;element of&quot; transform=&quot;translate(521, 0)&quot; id=&quot;MJX-0a687506f2d0a0fc4cf9693b366040a2-16&quot; aria-label=&quot;element of&quot; role=&quot;treeitem&quot;&gt;&lt;use xlink:href=&quot;#MJX-2447-TEX-N-2208&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;&lt;/use&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;g data-mml-node=&quot;mi&quot; data-semantic-type=&quot;identifier&quot; data-semantic-role=&quot;latinletter&quot; data-semantic-font=&quot;italic&quot; data-semantic-annotation=&quot;clearspeak:simple&quot; data-semantic-id=&quot;17&quot; data-semantic-parent=&quot;18&quot; data-semantic-speech=&quot;s&quot; transform=&quot;translate(1188, 0)&quot; id=&quot;MJX-0a687506f2d0a0fc4cf9693b366040a2-17&quot; aria-label=&quot;s&quot; role=&quot;treeitem&quot;&gt;&lt;use xlink:href=&quot;#MJX-2447-TEX-I-1D460&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;&lt;/use&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;g data-mml-node=&quot;msub&quot; data-semantic-type=&quot;subscript&quot; data-semantic-role=&quot;latinletter&quot; data-semantic-id=&quot;22&quot; data-semantic-children=&quot;20,21&quot; data-semantic-parent=&quot;30&quot; data-semantic-owns=&quot;20 21&quot; data-semantic-speech=&quot;x Subscript k Baseline&quot; transform=&quot;translate(1610.7, 0)&quot; id=&quot;MJX-0a687506f2d0a0fc4cf9693b366040a2-22&quot; aria-label=&quot;x Subscript k Baseline&quot; role=&quot;treeitem&quot; aria-owns=&quot;MJX-0a687506f2d0a0fc4cf9693b366040a2-20 MJX-0a687506f2d0a0fc4cf9693b366040a2-21&quot;&gt;&lt;g data-mml-node=&quot;mi&quot; data-semantic-type=&quot;identifier&quot; data-semantic-role=&quot;latinletter&quot; data-semantic-font=&quot;italic&quot; data-semantic-annotation=&quot;clearspeak:simple&quot; data-semantic-id=&quot;20&quot; data-semantic-parent=&quot;22&quot; data-semantic-speech=&quot;x&quot; data-semantic-prefix=&quot;Base&quot; id=&quot;MJX-0a687506f2d0a0fc4cf9693b366040a2-20&quot; aria-label=&quot;Base x&quot; role=&quot;treeitem&quot;&gt;&lt;use xlink:href=&quot;#MJX-2447-TEX-I-1D465&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;&lt;/use&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;g data-mml-node=&quot;mi&quot; transform=&quot;translate(572, -150) scale(0.707)&quot; data-semantic-type=&quot;identifier&quot; data-semantic-role=&quot;latinletter&quot; data-semantic-font=&quot;italic&quot; data-semantic-annotation=&quot;clearspeak:simple&quot; data-semantic-id=&quot;21&quot; data-semantic-parent=&quot;22&quot; data-semantic-speech=&quot;k&quot; data-semantic-prefix=&quot;Subscript&quot; id=&quot;MJX-0a687506f2d0a0fc4cf9693b366040a2-21&quot; aria-label=&quot;Subscript k&quot; role=&quot;treeitem&quot;&gt;&lt;use xlink:href=&quot;#MJX-2447-TEX-I-1D458&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;&lt;/use&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;g data-mml-node=&quot;mo&quot; data-semantic-type=&quot;punctuation&quot; data-semantic-role=&quot;vbar&quot; data-semantic-annotation=&quot;nemeth:number&quot; data-semantic-id=&quot;23&quot; data-semantic-parent=&quot;32&quot; data-semantic-operator=&quot;punctuated&quot; data-semantic-speech=&quot;vertical bar&quot; transform=&quot;translate(2601.1, 0)&quot; id=&quot;MJX-0a687506f2d0a0fc4cf9693b366040a2-23&quot; aria-label=&quot;vertical bar&quot; role=&quot;treeitem&quot;&gt;&lt;use xlink:href=&quot;#MJX-2447-TEX-N-7C&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;&lt;/use&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;g data-mml-node=&quot;mrow&quot; data-semantic-type=&quot;infixop&quot; data-semantic-role=&quot;unknown&quot; data-semantic-id=&quot;31&quot; data-semantic-children=&quot;24,28&quot; data-semantic-content=&quot;27&quot; data-semantic-parent=&quot;32&quot; data-semantic-owns=&quot;24 27 28&quot; data-semantic-speech=&quot;s subset of or equal to Subscript f Baseline omega&quot; transform=&quot;translate(2879.1, 0)&quot; id=&quot;MJX-0a687506f2d0a0fc4cf9693b366040a2-31&quot; aria-label=&quot;s subset of or equal to Subscript f Baseline omega&quot; role=&quot;treeitem&quot; aria-owns=&quot;MJX-0a687506f2d0a0fc4cf9693b366040a2-24 MJX-0a687506f2d0a0fc4cf9693b366040a2-27 MJX-0a687506f2d0a0fc4cf9693b366040a2-28&quot;&gt;&lt;g data-mml-node=&quot;mi&quot; data-semantic-type=&quot;identifier&quot; data-semantic-role=&quot;latinletter&quot; data-semantic-font=&quot;italic&quot; data-semantic-annotation=&quot;clearspeak:simple;nemeth:number&quot; data-semantic-id=&quot;24&quot; data-semantic-parent=&quot;31&quot; data-semantic-speech=&quot;s&quot; id=&quot;MJX-0a687506f2d0a0fc4cf9693b366040a2-24&quot; aria-label=&quot;s&quot; role=&quot;treeitem&quot;&gt;&lt;use xlink:href=&quot;#MJX-2447-TEX-I-1D460&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;&lt;/use&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;g data-mml-node=&quot;msub&quot; data-semantic-type=&quot;subscript&quot; data-semantic-role=&quot;unknown&quot; data-semantic-embellished=&quot;operator&quot; data-semantic-id=&quot;27&quot; data-semantic-children=&quot;25,26&quot; data-semantic-parent=&quot;31&quot; data-semantic-operator=&quot;infixop,⊆&quot; data-semantic-owns=&quot;25 26&quot; data-semantic-speech=&quot;subset of or equal to Subscript f Baseline&quot; transform=&quot;translate(746.8, 0)&quot; id=&quot;MJX-0a687506f2d0a0fc4cf9693b366040a2-27&quot; aria-label=&quot;subset of or equal to Subscript f Baseline&quot; role=&quot;treeitem&quot; aria-owns=&quot;MJX-0a687506f2d0a0fc4cf9693b366040a2-25 MJX-0a687506f2d0a0fc4cf9693b366040a2-26&quot;&gt;&lt;g data-mml-node=&quot;mo&quot; data-semantic-type=&quot;operator&quot; data-semantic-role=&quot;unknown&quot; data-semantic-id=&quot;25&quot; data-semantic-parent=&quot;27&quot; data-semantic-speech=&quot;subset of or equal to&quot; data-semantic-prefix=&quot;Base&quot; id=&quot;MJX-0a687506f2d0a0fc4cf9693b366040a2-25&quot; aria-label=&quot;Base subset of or equal to&quot; role=&quot;treeitem&quot;&gt;&lt;use xlink:href=&quot;#MJX-2447-TEX-N-2286&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;&lt;/use&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;g data-mml-node=&quot;mi&quot; transform=&quot;translate(778, -150) scale(0.707)&quot; data-semantic-type=&quot;identifier&quot; data-semantic-role=&quot;latinletter&quot; data-semantic-font=&quot;italic&quot; data-semantic-id=&quot;26&quot; data-semantic-parent=&quot;27&quot; data-semantic-speech=&quot;f&quot; data-semantic-prefix=&quot;Subscript&quot; id=&quot;MJX-0a687506f2d0a0fc4cf9693b366040a2-26&quot; aria-label=&quot;Subscript f&quot; role=&quot;treeitem&quot;&gt;&lt;use xlink:href=&quot;#MJX-2447-TEX-I-1D453&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;&lt;/use&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;g data-mml-node=&quot;mi&quot; data-semantic-type=&quot;identifier&quot; data-semantic-role=&quot;greekletter&quot; data-semantic-font=&quot;italic&quot; data-semantic-annotation=&quot;clearspeak:simple&quot; data-semantic-id=&quot;28&quot; data-semantic-parent=&quot;31&quot; data-semantic-speech=&quot;omega&quot; transform=&quot;translate(2241.5, 0)&quot; id=&quot;MJX-0a687506f2d0a0fc4cf9693b366040a2-28&quot; aria-label=&quot;omega&quot; role=&quot;treeitem&quot;&gt;&lt;use xlink:href=&quot;#MJX-2447-TEX-I-1D714&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;&lt;/use&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;g data-mml-node=&quot;mo&quot; data-semantic-type=&quot;fence&quot; data-semantic-role=&quot;close&quot; data-semantic-id=&quot;29&quot; data-semantic-parent=&quot;33&quot; data-semantic-operator=&quot;fenced&quot; data-semantic-speech=&quot;right brace&quot; transform=&quot;translate(6548.5, 0)&quot; id=&quot;MJX-0a687506f2d0a0fc4cf9693b366040a2-29&quot; aria-label=&quot;right brace&quot; role=&quot;treeitem&quot;&gt;&lt;use xlink:href=&quot;#MJX-2447-TEX-S4-7D&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;&gt;&lt;/use&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;span hidden=&quot;&quot;&gt;\operatorname{FS}(x_i)_{i\in \omega} = \left\{ \sum_{k \in s} x_k | s \subseteq_f \omega \right\}
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/mjx-container&gt;</content>
	</entry>
</feed>
